<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A disswasive from error much increased a perswasive to order much decayed / by Joseph Bentham.</title>
            <author>Bentham, Joseph, 1594?-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 220 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27412</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1909</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25276</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08834103</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08834103</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41930</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27412)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41930)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1274:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A disswasive from error much increased a perswasive to order much decayed / by Joseph Bentham.</title>
                  <author>Bentham, Joseph, 1594?-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 86 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by William Thompson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Apostasy.</term>
               <term>Faith.</term>
               <term>Offenses against religion.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41930:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A DISSWASIVE FROM ERROR Much INCREASED.</p>
            <p>A PERSWASIVE TO ORDER Much DECAYED.</p>
            <p>By a Lover of, and Labourer for Truth, Peace, Unity, Una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity, Uniformity and Order, <hi>Joſeph Bentham.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>JUDE 3.</bibl>
               <p>Earneſtly contend for the faith which was once delivered to the Saints.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>William Thompſon,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Harborow,</hi> 1669.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41930:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:41930:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O prevent prejudice in thoſe who ſhall read theſe following Diſcourſes of Error and Order, I think it expedient to premiſe four following particulars.</p>
            <p>Whereas I have made uſe of many paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> out of Authors, and not ſhewed of<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Melanc.</hi> pag. 8.</note> whom and whereof, I confeſs it, ſo that I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt may ſay with Mr. <hi>Burton,</hi> all is mine, and none mine; As a good Houſe-wife out of divers fleeces weaves one piece of cloth, and as a Bee gathereth wax and honey out of many flowers, and makes a new lump; for I in penning this I now publiſh, I did like him, who out of divers gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens gathers a Poſie, taking here and there a flower for his own uſe in his own houſe, for a day and then layeth it aſide, being regardleſs from whoſe garden he had each particular flower. So I gathering many paſſages out of Authors for mine own uſe, for that time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending then to lay them aſide, regarded not much where and of whom I borrowed to make up my Work; for had I purpoſed to have done that I now do (by a kind of neceſſity, and the deſire of ſome) I had filled my Margent more, as in this Preface, and the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Poſtſcript.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41930:3"/>
            <p> If any ſay I have mentioned old faults, after the act of Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> which I ſhould not have done, I confeſs it. But Mr. <hi>Caryl</hi> aſſures me, That a man may rationally remember the wrong ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">On <hi>Job</hi> 11. 16.</note> hath done him, with all the circumſtances and paſſages of it, yet forget it ſpiritually: <hi>Forget it</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſo far as to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give it fully, and then remember it as much as you will.</hi> Thus I have done, and ſhall do. 2. To do the work of the day up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the day, I muſt make mention of ſome ſuch things, namely, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 30 day of <hi>January,</hi> to work humiliation in my ſelf &amp; others; and upon the 29 day of <hi>May</hi> to ſtir up my ſelf and others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o rejoyce and give thanks. 3. But what if there are who juſtifie ſuch their f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rmer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffences; muſt we then be ſilent, and ſo conſent that they do well? We muſt not leave reproving, if men will not leave ſinning. Men indeed deal hardly with us, who impute that as a fault to us which was our duty to do. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to convince men of error is a duty; yea, although men diſpoſed to reſiſt will hardly ever be convinced. And friends may debate, and not abate of their affection, ſtriving for verity, not m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtery, ſeeking for truth, not praiſe or victory,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <hi>Mr.</hi> Henderſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> as our famous Martyr <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng Charls</hi> ſaith.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Some perhaps think I ſo spe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k, as if moſt were in thoſe kinds <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> offenders; if ſo, I think they may blame Saint <hi>Paul</hi> as well as me, who ſo writes to the <hi>Galatians</hi> and <hi>Corinthians,</hi> blaming only the faulty, ſo I blame only, and labour to better the faulty; not that the greateſt number are ſuch; for in my Pariſh there are who are orderly, &amp; conform<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble to the Church, yea ſuch who have ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their loyalty, and continue loyal; yet there are others, and<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sacra ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta regum Majeſtas,</hi> pag. 64 Of civ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of <hi>England,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ag 91. <hi>Melanc.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ag. 610. Pag 166. Pag. 31. Anſwer to <hi>Worc.</hi> pape<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, p. 137.</note> if but two, too many by two, who cannot be excuſed from thoſe former actings, of which <hi>I. A.</hi> ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th, <hi>No perſecution that ever was, can parallel this perſecution for impiety, injuſtice and cruelty.</hi> Such who (as <hi>Henry</hi> Earl of <hi>Monmouth</hi> ſaith) <hi>are quiet, when they know not how to diſquiet others:</hi> Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h who (as Mr. <hi>Burton</hi> ſaith) <hi>are ever mending Churches, States, Superiors, mending all ſave themſelves.</hi> Such to whom may be applyed a ſaying of Cardinal <hi>Bentivoglio,</hi> writing of the Wars of <hi>Flanders, Clemency in Princes ſerves to lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle purpoſe, when obſtinacy and diſloyalty of Subjects is thereby made greater.</hi> And that of <hi>Curia Politiae, Cruelty may make Subjects miſerable, Clemency may make them</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:41930:3"/> 
               <hi>criminal.</hi> Such of whom <hi>Hamondle Strang</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of prim. devot. pag. 164.</note> 
               <hi>to pardon nothing, it is double cruelty to pardon all.</hi> Such of whom Mr. <hi>Edward Sparks</hi> his ſaying is verified, Zeal without knowledge, and charity as now adayes, (As they without zeal are like glow-worms, having ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me cold ſplendor without heat) blind me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l'd horſes, ſo far like the fire of hell, that burn, and have no ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Such who complain much of ſin abounding, and blame Prea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers for not preaching more ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inſt ſin: but if ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the practiſe of Chriſt and the Apoſtles, they preach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe Prophets in ſheeps-cloathing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 15. againſt hypocriſie, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. against reſiſting of Authority, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. to beware of cauſers of diviſions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 18. not to reſt in a form of god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ineſs, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 5. not to have itching ears, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 3, 4. not to deſpiſe dominions, <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de</hi> 6. Then they are ready to complain of railing, and ſpeaking againſt God's people, and well-affected, and reſolve to hear ſuch Preachers no more, little conſidering that in ſo ſaying they ſhew palpab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir own guilt; for I am ſure, and dare confidently affirm, That the more g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y and well<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>affected people are, the further they are from, &amp; the more they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hor Hypocr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſie, Diſobedience, Rebellion, S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſms, F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns, and ſuch like, being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f all m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the moſt obedient, ſincere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceable and quiet.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If any blame me for mentioning wrongs done to my ſelf, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> I anſwer; 1. I d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it without any revengeful or malicious intent, which I hope is cleered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y my manner of ſpeech, and by my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer carriage ſince my re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urn; I being of <hi>Gregories</hi> mind,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Melanc.</hi> p. 328.</note> whom Mr. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rton</hi> affirms to ſay, <hi>He who cannot bear inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries againſt himſelf is no good man.</hi> And being able through<note place="margin">Pag. 4.</note> God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mercy to ſay with Sir <hi>Edward Deering, I thank God my heart hath never known the ſetling of a perſonal malice;</hi> Well knowing, <hi>That revenge</hi> (as <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cholas Cauſin</hi> tell us) <hi>is proper to weak minds, whereas clemency alwayes reſideth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>in a ſtrong ſpirit.</hi> 2. Beſides, I c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld not well avoid it; for al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hough ſome, as <hi>Strada</hi> ſaith, are cured by contempt, yet <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag 7.</note> 
               <hi>Medicatus</hi> tells us, <hi>It is the method of charity to ſuffer without retortion in particular wrongs, but not when Gods glory is in queſtion.</hi> Chriſt pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yed for them who perſecuted him, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pt them who diſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oured his fat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers houſe, to ſuffer God
<pb facs="tcp:41930:4"/> to be wronged, and not moved, is not charity but luke-warmneſs and ſtupidity. I endeavouring to wipe off the diſhonouring of God, and ſcandalizing his Goſpel, and the Proteſtant Religion, caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it by ſuch mens contemning and ſleighting Gods Ordinances, vilifying his meſſengers as ſcandalous and unprofitable, preferring unwarranted Conventicles before the publick worſhip of God, and by blemiſhing the famous Government and Church of <hi>England</hi> as unchriſtian and perſecuting, was conſtrained to mention as I have done. 3. And in thus doing I imitate a good Preſident, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who names in his writings, eſpecially to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> his own ſufferings, and from them alſo. For my ſelf, I was glad I had ſuch a living to loſe for ſo good a cauſe, and an heart ſo willing to part with it. I in ſo doing finding the truth of a ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Miniſters portion. p. 208.</note> in Dr. <hi>Sclater, Affliction is the beſt tutor to devotion.</hi> And ſuch experiences of Gods mercies to me and mine, that I was (as all who knew me can teſtifie) patient, content and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. And ſince my return, which is eighty ears, I have not ſhewed the leaſt diſlike to thoſe who outed me; and therefore now being ſcarce able to go, and ſhortly to end my pilgrimage, I hope I ſhall cheriſh no ſuch helliſh vermin as malice and deſire of revenge in my heart, but endeavour to live with ſuch love and peace, which are the furtherers to that future love, peace and joy which are for ever.</p>
            <p>Should any queſtion why I make ſo much uſe of Mr. <hi>Ball,</hi> and ſome old Non-Conformiſts, of Mr. <hi>Bayly</hi> and other later Presbyterians, moſt men without my telling may conjecture rightly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecauſe ſuch mens ſayings will ſooner prevail with thoſe I deal withal, than of the Fathers and other Divines. As alſo becauſe men may ſee the vaſt difference betwixt them, and thoſe whoſe ſo lowers they pretend to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, when in truth they are followers of Mr. <hi>Barrow, Greenwood,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ſuch of the ſeparation, who had Mr. <hi>Ball,</hi> Mr. <hi>Brinſly,</hi> &amp;c. old Non-Conformiſts, Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bayly,</hi> &amp;c. late Presbyterians, their great oppoſers.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41930:4"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>JAM. 1. 16.</bibl>
                        <p>Do not err my Beloved Brethren.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE three laſt Lords dayes I preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto you of conſcience; I ſhewed you what it is, the kinds of it, how it is God's Officer, what its duty is, and what its rule. That we are not to take all for conſcience which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to be ſo. And ſince conſcience is in every one, and it will live with us for ever, that we ſhould be careful to have our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſuch, that we and they may have peace and comfort; and that for this end we ſhould endeavour to have our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences enlightned, faithful, lively, and not blind, ſlothful, dead, or erroneous; therefore I purpoſe to ſhew you what it is to err, the danger of error, and in the words of St. <hi>James</hi> diſſwade you from it; <hi>Do not err,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle having diſſwaded from thinking God to be the Author of ſin (an horrid blaſphemy) he perſwades them<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 176. Iſa. 63. 17.</note> not to err or wander, a Metaphor taken from ſheep go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſtray. Errors are of two ſorts. 1. In practiſe, going from the Word, the Rule of righteouſneſs, erring from God's wayes. 2. In judgment, going off from the Word as the ſtandard and meaſure of truth, which we commonly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41930:5"/> call error. To make way to what I intend, I will lay down ſome few Propoſitions.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="proposition">
                     <head>I. Propoſition.</head>
                     <p>The firſt, That error is common to man, ever ſince the fall of man. It is evident how <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> erred, and how their poſterity ſmart for it is manifeſt, yea how their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity were polluted with error we ſee in <hi>Cain,</hi> and in the old world, for which the Lord ſent the Deluge. After which, errors ſo abounded, that Languages were confounded, <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha</hi> turned into aſhes. After the Lord choſe <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m</hi> and his ſeed to be his peculiar people, they ſoon erred in <hi>Egypt,</hi> in the Wilderneſs, and in <hi>Canaan,</hi> worſhipping Calves, and <hi>Baal,</hi> yea ſacrificing their children to Devils. When our Saviour Chriſt was upon earth, how oft doth he check for erring, not knowing the Scriptures? How oft doth he confute the errors of the Scribes, Phariſees, and Saduces? What warnings and caveats doth he give to us<note place="margin">Mat. 7. 15. Mat. 24. 24. Act. 8. 9, 13, 18. 2 Tim. 2. i7 Rev. 2. 14, 15, 20. 2 Cor. 11. 13. Gal. 3. 1. Phil. 3. 1. Rom. 16. 17. Eph 4. 14. 1 Tim. 4. 2 2 Tim. 3. 1, 2. 2 Tim. 4. 3</note> to beware of falſe Prophets in ſheeps cloathing, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint us with the danger of ſuch. After our Saviours aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending into heaven, errors did abound notwithſtanding the pains and piety of the Apoſtles. <hi>Simon Magus</hi> bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the people, <hi>Elymas</hi> alſo, with <hi>Hymineus</hi> and <hi>Philetus.</hi> Some in the <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches held the doctrine of <hi>Balaam,</hi> ſome of the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> and ſome the filthy follies of <hi>Jezabel.</hi> The <hi>Corinthians</hi> were drawn from the doctrine of the truth by falſe Apoſtles. The <hi>Gal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tians</hi> bewitched from the truth. The <hi>Philippians</hi> in great danger. The <hi>Romans</hi> ſtaggered with ſuch who cauſed diviſions, and the <hi>Epheſians</hi> ſubject to be carried about with every wind of doctrine. The Apoſtle alſo foretels of ſwarms of errors which ſhould be, and how men will not endure ſound doctrine, but after their luſts heap to themſelves teachers, having itching ears, turning their ears from the truth, and be turned to fables. Since which, all ages ſhew how this was fulfilled, for in the firſt hundred years after Chriſt, many groſs errors abounded, as the <hi>Symoniani</hi> of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> the <hi>Hyminei</hi> of <hi>Hymineus</hi>
                        <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41930:5"/> and <hi>Philetus.</hi> The <hi>Nazareni</hi> ſo called of the City <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">See <hi>opus Epiphanii de Hare<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſib. Augustin. de Haereſib. Tom.</hi> 8.</note> The <hi>Menandriani</hi> of <hi>Menander,</hi> Scholar to <hi>Magus.</hi> The <hi>Ebionites</hi> of <hi>Ebion</hi> whom St. <hi>John</hi> confuted. The <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laitans</hi> of <hi>Nicholas</hi> one of the ſeven Deacons. The <hi>Cerinthii</hi> of <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> whom St. <hi>John</hi> called the firſt-born of Satan. The <hi>Saturniani</hi> of <hi>Saturnus.</hi> The <hi>Baſilidians</hi> of <hi>Baſilides,</hi> &amp;c. In the ſecond century after Chriſt there ſprung up above thirty ſeveral ſorts, of which number were the <hi>Maritae</hi> of <hi>Marus,</hi> who called themſelves perfect, yea more perfect than <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul.</hi> They denied Chriſt's taking humane nature, and the reſurrection of the fleſh. About this time alſo aroſe the <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> ſo called, becauſe of their excellent knowledge in their own opinions, although but vain. By others they were called <hi>Barbaritae,</hi> becauſe of their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and filthineſs. They fancied two ſouls in each good man, one holy of the ſubſtance of God, the other adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious, which is in man as in other creatures. They taught the being of two Gods, the one good, the other evil. That Martyrdom was not to be undertaken for Chriſt. They worſhipped the Images of Chriſt, and had images in as great eſteem as Pagans their Gods. In the third Century there aroſe about twenty ſorts of Hereſies, of which I will name two. The <hi>Cathariſts</hi> ſo called from their ſanctity in their own opinion; they gloried of merits, of their good works; they denied repentance to ſuch who fell through in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity, and condemned ſecond marriages as unlawful. The <hi>Donatiſts</hi> alſo of <hi>Donatus,</hi> who affirmed the Church of God on earth to be without ſpot. None to be compelled to live well. Hereticks not to be repreſſed by Magiſtrates. That the worthineſs of the Sacrament is from the holineſs of him who gives it. That perſons baptized by the Orthodox are to be rebaptized. That killing themſelves to avoid puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for their errors is Martyrdom. They ſaid the Son was inferiour to the Father, the holy Ghoſt to the Son, and they boaſted of Revelations.</p>
                     <p>In the fourth Century aroſe above twenty, of which the <hi>Pelagians</hi> was one, of <hi>Pelagius,</hi> who taught that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould have died if he had not ſinned. That <hi>Adams</hi> ſin did hurt only
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41930:6"/> himſelf. That there is no Original ſin. That men have free will ſufficient to do well; and that God gives grace to the merits of works.</p>
                     <p>The fifth Century had ſome, and the ſixth brought forth, as ſome others, ſo thoſe grand errors of <hi>Mahumetaniſm</hi> and Papiſm.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mahumetaniſm</hi> of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> which hath overſpread many Kingdoms under the <hi>Turk</hi> and other Kings. They deny the being of perſons in the Trinity. They ſay God is corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real. That Chriſt was not God, but a creature, yet a great Prophet. That Chriſt did not ſuffer, nor was not crucified. That the Devil in the end ſhall be ſaved. That Eternal Life conſiſts in bodily pleaſures. They obſerve Circumciſion, Waſhings, with ſome other Judaical Ceremonies. They ſwear by Creatures, and War for Religion, to which they ſay men are to be compelled. They allow of many Wives, and Divorce without cauſe. They hope to be ſaved by works. They deny pardon for ever to them who forſake their Religion. They hold venial and mortal ſins. They pray towards the Eaſt, a ſet number daily, but not for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers. And they take away the Sacraments ordained by Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Papiſm</hi> aroſe under <hi>Phoca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> the Emperor, and <hi>Boniface</hi> the third, Popes of <hi>Rome. Luther</hi> was born at <hi>Iſleben</hi> in <hi>Saxony,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Sleidan. Anab.</note> 1483. He when <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth ſent forth pardons, 1516. op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed them. Preaching in <hi>Saxony,</hi> there aroſe <hi>Nicolas Stocks,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Muncer,</hi> preaching that goods ſhould be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. Upon this fourty thouſand roſe in <hi>Suevia</hi> and <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conia,</hi> plundering and killing; but the Princes arming, took <hi>Frantus,</hi> executed <hi>Muncer, Phifer,</hi> and hundreds more. The City <hi>Munſter</hi> having received the Goſpel, <hi>John Bec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ld</hi> a Taylor, came from <hi>Leyden</hi> thither, where keeping Conventicles, in few months he gets a great party, they obtain freedom for their Religion, and after grow ſo ſtrong as to drive all the Proteſtants out. This <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> is made King, he gave leave to have many W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ves, himſelf took fifteen. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vanquiſhed, he with <hi>Knipperdoling,</hi> were tyed to a ſtake, their fleſh pul'd in pieces with hot p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ncers; he recanted his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41930:6"/> errors, <hi>Knipperdoling</hi> did not, but died like a mad man. Theſe Anabaptiſts maintained, as Mr. <hi>Paget</hi> ſhews us, ten errors not to be tollerated in the Church; Four not to be ſuffered in a Common-wealth, and three not in a Family, as community of goods, putting away of Wives of a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Religion, and that Chriſtians may have many Wives. Thouſands of theſe periſhed in <hi>Germany</hi> by the ſword; and in Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>een <hi>Eliza<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eths</hi> time ſome of them in <hi>England</hi> recanted, and ſome were burnt.</p>
                     <p>After theſe aroſe the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> called Separatiſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Paget.</hi>
                        </note> they ſeparate from all reformed Churches, then one from another. <hi>Robert Brown,</hi> School-maſter in <hi>Southwark,</hi> preached in a gravel-pit neer <hi>Iſlington,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> refuſed to talk with him, Mr. <hi>Greenham</hi> perſwaded him, but could not prevail, ſo to little purpoſe; for he led his company be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea, where (ſeeing their diviſions) he left them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned into <hi>England,</hi> took the Parſonage of a Church in <hi>Northamptonſhire</hi> and died, as I have been informed, ſince the beginning of our late troubles. He and his followers left our Church, as they ſaid, for our many abominations.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Barrowiſts</hi> following yet more; they compared our Church to <hi>Sodom, Babylon, Egypt,</hi> as <hi>Barrow, Brewis, Bois, Rutter,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Wilkinſonians</hi> went a ſtep higher, affirming they were the Apoſtles, and denied Communion to all who would not give them that title.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Paget.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Lemmariſts</hi> maintained a monſter of Hereſies. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humetaniſm</hi> denying the Trinity and the eternal Godhead of Chriſt. <hi>Jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iſm</hi> affirming Chriſt to come ſhortly to reign on the earth. <hi>Papiſm</hi> affirming a meer creature may be worſhipped. <hi>Lutheraniſm</hi> maintaining conſubſtantiation. <hi>Anabaptiſm</hi> affirming that Chriſt took not fleſh of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary. Libertiniſm</hi> holding no viſible Church on earth. <hi>Browniſm</hi> holding ſeparation, ſeparating from all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, excommunicating and curſing on another. Mr. <hi>Paget</hi> alſo tells us, that the begining of the Independents was thus. Mr. <hi>Robinſon</hi> leaving <hi>Norwich</hi> in diſcontent, became a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid <hi>Browniſt,</hi> but after by conference with ſome learned
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41930:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> men, he recanted his opinions, yet derived this his way of Independency to his ſeparate Congregation at <hi>Leyden;</hi> and part of that Congregation did carry it to <hi>Plymouth</hi> in new <hi>England,</hi> where the aſhes of Independency did break out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a burning flame. And Mr. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>yly</hi> ſets down the fruits of<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Bayly.</hi>
                        </note> this Independency in new <hi>England</hi> (in the opinions of ſome, for I ſuppoſe he ſpeaks not of all, there being amongſt them many ſober Miniſters and Magiſtrates, who oppoſed and overthrew thoſe opinions. And they refuſing to own the late powers, is an Argument of their ſobriety. Beſides, there hath been great converſion of the <hi>Indians,</hi> in ſo much that the Bible is tranſlated and Printed in their Tongue, as I am informed.) How it placeth many thouſands of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in the condition of Pagans; how it marr'd the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of Pagans to Chriſtian Religion; how it brought forth the fouleſt Hereſies that ever yet were heard of in any Proteſtant Church, to the number of fourſcore and eleven. That their piety ſeemed ſingular; their malice was ſingular againſt all who oppoſed them, eſpecially Orthodox Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. That their contempt of Magiſtrates was grievous, their errors in opinion did draw on ſuch ſeditious practiſes, which did well near overturn both their Church and State. That their proud obſtinacy againſt all admonitions was marvellous, that in the midſt of their profeſſion of piety, the prophanity of many of them was great. Of theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars he ſpeak largely, and ſhews his warrant for what he ſaith in many particulars. In Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, Mr. <hi>Barrow, Greenwood, Percy,</hi> and ſome others were executed. <hi>Studly, Billet</hi> and <hi>Bowly</hi> had judgment to be ſo. The firſt Propoſition is clearly evident, <hi>That men, yea the best of men, are ſubject to err (humanum eſt errare)</hi> and have need to be called on not to err; for they who have moſt light here, have much darkneſs in them, and we are more prone to follow the darkneſs of our ſpirits, than the light of Gods Spirit. He who thinks he cannot err, reckons himſelf more than a man; for whilſt there remains corruption in the will, the underſtanding cannot be wholly free from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. The wills, affections, and underſtandings of Saints
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41930:7"/> on earth have ſome corruption remaining in them; as their practiſe, ſo their opinions are ſoyld and faulty; yea often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times good men continue long in error. <hi>Jobs</hi> friends did multiply, but not mend their anſwers; for as it is hard to part<note place="margin">Job 21. 34</note> with an evil practiſe, ſo and much more with an ill opinion, &amp;c. error in opinion, becauſe that reflects on the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the beſt faculty, the judgment. And therefore we ſhould be as careful to avoid errors as other vices: Since a blind eye may be as bad as a lame foot; ſince a man wanting light is apt to fall and ſtumble; and the Apoſtle ſhews, that<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 26.</note> a vain mind hath vain affections.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="proposition">
                     <head>II. Propoſition.</head>
                     <p>The ſecond Propoſition is this. <hi>Although many men who know much do greatly err, yet error and ignorance are of ſo neer kin, that ignorance is uſually the mother of error.</hi> An ignorant man may be ſtubborn and wilful, yet he cannot be fixt and<note place="margin">Mat. 22. 29.</note> ſteddy, but is doubtful and wavering, yet prone to ſettle himſelf in that which is unſound, ſo ſubject to error. If a knowing man doth err, it is hard to convince him; and if he who knows no reaſon doth err, he will not be convinced by reaſon. Surely error properly proceeds from ignorance; for he who maintains either opinion or practiſe againſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, is more than in an error. It is obſtinacy when it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to practiſe, it is Hereſie when it refers to opinion; for in Hereticks errors are uſually againſt light, and ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in error.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="proposition">
                     <head>III. Propoſition.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>He who judgeth himſelf to be in the truth, is not to leave the truth becauſe ſome call it error; for as we are not to take up errors becauſe ſome call them truths, ſo we are not to let go truths becauſe ſome call them errors.</hi> Good men ſhould be eaſily led into the<note place="margin">Prov. 22. 23. Iſa. 11. 6.</note> right way, and turn to the truth, but not forced from it, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things being called errors which are not. A man therefore not convinced (and deſirous to be informed) he is out of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41930:8"/> way; nothing ſaid to ſatisfie conſcience, and to change his jugment; much ſpoken, but little proved; many reaſons in number, all light in weight, he is not to leave the truth judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to be ſo. And men ſhould be careful not to brand ſuch for errors which are not, or they think to be ſo, except, and until they can prove them to be ſo; which Chriſt doth, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving reaſons, and making good his charge; for invectives do<note place="margin">Mat. 23. 13, 14. &amp;c</note> no good, diſcoveries may. We are to make good our charge when we accuſe any of error or hereſie, many being falſly accuſed as we are by Papiſts, who ſpread the livery of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks and Schiſmaticks on us. Innocent truths often ſuffer under odious imputations. To prove error therefore, we are to be more in argument than in paſſion; to condemn things by reaſoning, not miſcalling.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="proposition">
                     <head>IV. Propoſition.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Although men do uſually offend towards ſuch who do err, uſing bitter ſpeeches againſt them they think are in error, yea then when they cannot prove it an error; as</hi> Jobs <hi>friends had many hards words againſt</hi> Job, <hi>few or no ſound Arguments; it being eaſier to be angry with an error, than to argue againſt it, and men are uſually ſo angry, becauſe they have little reaſon, they often having moſt earneſtneſs againſt opinions, who have leaſt to ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</hi> Moreover, although they who ſuppoſe us to be in error do therefore magnifie themſelves againſt us, and in ſo doing come under the Apoſtles reproof, they ſinning in<note place="margin">Rom. 11. 17, 18, 14. 3. 1 Cor. 10. 11.</note> ſo doing; 1. Becauſe they forget their own frailties, and how apt they are to fall (whereas by others failings we ſhould take notice to what we may be tempted, as by others holy actions we are to learn what we ſhould do) and becauſe ſuch forget that they have fallen into other ſins and errors, if not the ſame: Yea, ſuppoſe they are freer than is poſſible<note place="margin">Joh. 8. 5.</note> to be on earth, why ſhould they magnifie themſelves over others who ſin? Doth God ſo? O no, he pities and ſpares! Bewail we then their condition, pray for them, and bleſs God who hath preſerved us. It being no eaſie matter to convince ſuch who err, error being as binding as truth, not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41930:8"/> in the name of error, but of truth, men being in love with their own conceptions, which are as the fleſh of their own minds. And men taking up an opinion, think it a diſgrace to lay it down again; it being alſo a rare thing to make men yield up their judgments although miſguided. When there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we deal with erroneous perſons, it is good to follow the Apoſtles direction, inſtructing oppoſers with meekneſs,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 25.</note> ſince gentle dealings will beſt become diſſwaſives from er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror; for where the matter is like to diſpleaſe, the manner ſhould not be ſharp. Bitter pills muſt be ſugar'd, that they may go down the better, otherwiſe men of contrary minds will think all ſpoken againſt them to be out of rage &amp; anger. And other offendors will better abide ſharpneſs than they; for contrary opinions think they are in the right, and pride is touchy; whereas other ſins fill the ſoul with ſhame, and there is not that boldneſs to reply; whereas in opin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ons, where men think they are in the right, we have need to deal gently, leſt pride take prejudice; according therefore to St. <hi>Pauls</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, and St. <hi>James</hi> his practiſe, <hi>I beſeech you brethren do not err.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="proposition">
                     <head>V. Propoſition.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>We are to be careful not to live in, or m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>intain any error in our ſelves; and in our ſeveral places we ſhould endeavour to draw o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Jam. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 19, 20.</note> 
                        <hi>from their errors, turning men from the error of their wayes.</hi> This is a duty, and needful, ſince good men are ſubject to err,<note place="margin">Mat. 24. 24.</note> error being catching, and much comply<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ng with our natural thoughts; we being alſo to take care of others ſalvation, one member of the ſafety of another; yea, of the meaneſt in the<note place="margin">Hab. 3. 12. 11. 15, 16. Exo. 23. 4.</note> Church, one ſpark oft occaſioning a great flame. It being alſo an act of charity to reduce thoſe who go aſtray, even a ſtraying beaſt, much more a man (although uſually none are ſo angry as they who are ſeduced into opinions by intereſt, their ſores muſt not be touched) for to maintain an error is<note place="margin">Gal. 4. 15.</note> a vain thing, nothing being more vain than errors, or falſe opinions of God, of the wayes of God, and of his dealings. Error is vanity, it is a lye. He therefore who is in an error<note place="margin">1 Joh. 2. 21.</note>
                        <pb n="10" facs="tcp:41930:9"/> ſhould be convinced, although ſome will make a fair cover for a deformed error, there being no error but ſome will ſecond; yea, and ſome mens conſciences when they know not what to ſay will be talkative, although it is an ill office to be Orators for our own or others errors, our own or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſinful practiſes; conſidering alſo how ſubject man is to err in ſpeech, practiſe and judgment. And that men knowing they may err, are in a fairer way to the truth, than ſuch who think they cannot err, they erring in ſo thinking, whereas ſuch are moſt ſecured from error who think they may err.</p>
                     <p>Errors alſo in doctrine are uſually accompanied with er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in life. The groſs prophaneſs of the <hi>Browniſts</hi> is ſhewed in a Book called the prophane Schiſms of the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> and by Mr. <hi>Paget,</hi> from the teſtimony of the <hi>Dutch Church,</hi> and of the Magiſtrates of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> inſtancing in <hi>Studley, Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker, Holder,</hi> and others, yea in Mr. <hi>Brown</hi> himſelf, who being reproved for beating his Wife, ſaid, <hi>He did not beat his Wife, but a curſt old Woman.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moreover, ſince errors will have the worſt at laſt, they cannot hold out, truth will prevail; and ſince ſuch who maintain errors ſhall not find favour with God. <hi>Jobs</hi> friends<note place="margin">Job 42. 7.</note> held an error unknown, and for zeal to God, yet God was angry with them, and is with ſuch, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 19.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, Conſidering that many errors are damnable, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal,<note place="margin">Jam. 5. 19, 20.</note> deadly; a freeing from them being a freeing from death, our care ſhould be not to dally with them, there being death in them; as the way of truth is the way of life, ſo alſo to draw others from them, and ſo procure their converſion and<note place="margin">Act. 4. 12. Joh. 17. 3.</note> pardon, for none can be ſaved without Chriſt. Such who are ſaved by Chriſt muſt know him, and believe in him, and we muſt believe in him according to the tenour of Scripture, the rule of faith, and not err from it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                        </label> If we do err, ours are but ſmall errors.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> Differences about leſſer points of Doctrine, of Scripture held up for by ends againſt conſcience may be damnable, for then a leſſer opinion is in the ſame rank with a known ſin; and ſo an error may be damnable by circumſtance; a man<note place="margin">Joh. 3. 19.</note> walking againſt light, be the error but ſmall, the danger is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41930:9"/> great, if a walking againſt light. And groſs negligence, or not taking pains to know better is equivalent to ſtanding out againſt the light; it arguing a ſecret fear and ſuſpition of the truth. And ſuch men who live and die in leſs errors about<note place="margin">Joh. 3. 20. 2 Pet. 3. 5. 1 Cor. 3. 13.</note> faith and worſhip, being willingly ignorant, if they be ſaved, they may expect to be ſaved with much difficulty (by fire) as loſs of much comfort, of much peace, being ſcorched in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and kept in dark and doubtful wayes.</p>
                     <p>Theſe things thus premiſed, I will ſhew you what an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>error is, what it is to err. Error ſtrictly and properly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, is that which men hold or do out of ignorance of the truth. It is in practiſe when we are ignorant of what is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be done; it is in opinion when we are ignorant of what is better for us to believe or hold. Error then is an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion<note place="margin">Mat. 22. 29.</note> or action ſwerving from the Rule of Gods Word; when that which is falſe is believed to be true, contrary to the mind of him from whom we ſay we have received it; as if a man ſhould believe idols to be Gods, becauſe Scripture calls them ſo. It is an error when a thing which is falſe is believed to be true, becauſe he from whom we received it, thinks it is true: Should a man think the ſoul was made of moats, becauſe <hi>Lucretius</hi> thought ſo, and we read it in him. It is an error, When out of another mans writings ſome true thing is believed, which he who wrote it did not believe; as to think an Epicure did place good in continency becauſe he praiſed it. It is an error. Error is a wandring or ſtraying<note place="margin">Act. 10. 45</note> from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> right way; it is hardly cured, being very preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent;<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2. 11. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>A ſcopo aberrare,</hi> to ſwerve from the mark. Gal. 5. 20.</note> and it is the way to Hereſie, although it is not Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. Hereſie being an error and more. Hereſie muſt be in ſome fundamental point or truth; it takes men off from Chriſt, or from the foundation of ſaving knowledge. It is accompanied with pertinacy and obſtinacy, after cleer light offered; it is poſſible to have an error about ſome funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental point, yet be no Heretick. Hereſie makes men take pleaſure and delight in it, therefore it is called a work of the<note place="margin">Tit. 3. 10.</note> fleſh, and ſuch are often wounded by themſelves, although they will not be convinced by others. Hereſie being an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in judgment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a pertinacy in will, and a taking delight in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41930:10"/> it in our affections, ſo an error, and more; we are the more careful to take heed of it, ſince ſuch like tares are ſown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Gods wheat, yea while the Apoſtles lived; and the cauſes of it ſtill remains; namely, ignorance of God, pride of heart, ſelf-conceitedneſs, want of love to Chriſt, and his truth; Satans malice, ambition, covetouſneſs, flattery, and Gods permitting ſuch ſtill for trial of his; as gold by fire, for the cleerer confirming of the truth, and for the puniſhment of the contempt of his truth, and careleſs entertainment of<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2. 11.</note> his word. It is no wonder then, if after a faithful Paſtor there comes a Wolf.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="question">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                        </label> If any doth ask why God permits deceivers to draw men into errors, and men to be drawn into them?</head>
                     <p n="1">
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> 1. Scripture ſhews it is for the tryal of his, to ſhew the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption or ſincerity which is in men.<note place="margin">Deut 13. i, 2, 3. 1 Cor. 11. 19. Jude 3.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. To make his to contend for the faith. Some are buſie to ſpread errors, that others may be buſie to withſtand them, to avoid them. A Cut-purſe is like another man, yet when men are aſſured ſuch are in the crowd, every one will look to his purſe: So when errors are abroad, every one ſhould take more heed to himſelf.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. God often puniſheth one ſin by another. Men continuing in ſins of practiſe, God ſuffers them often to fall into ſinful<note place="margin">Ezek. 14. 7. 2 Theſ. 2. 11.</note> opinions; falſe doctrines are fit plagues for falſe hearts. They who love not the truth are puniſhed with belief of errors; and ſuch are ſore puniſhments which are made of ſins.</p>
                     <p>That we may therefore avoid error,<note n="(1)" place="margin">Pſal. 25. 9.</note> Be we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.<note n="(2)" place="margin">John 7. 17.</note> Be diligent in obeying the Word.<note n="(3)" place="margin">Pſal. 119. 113. Tit. 3. 10.</note> Grow up in love to the affecting of the truth. Take heed of Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Books, and of company with ſuch perſons, they being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious; take heed of covetouſneſs and ambition, which have made many Hereticks, and reject thoſe who are ſuch.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                        </label> You ſaid from <hi>Timothy,</hi> that they are mildly, lovingly, and tenderly to be dealt withal, How then reject?</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> They are ſo, whilſt there is hopes they may be gained and won; for in ſo doing we imitate God, who admoniſheth<note place="margin">Gal. 6. 1.</note> before he ſmites. He commands alſo to reſtore with meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41930:10"/> and by ſo doing we ſhew our great love to the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, and imitate St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who uſed not the rod ſo long as meekneſs would prevail. Such places therefore as <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 17. 2. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. are to be underſtood after admonitions, and good means uſed for their reclaiming, which proving vain, they are to be rejected. In regard of themſelves.<note n="(1)" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5. 5.</note> To work ſorrow for their ſin.<note n="(2)" place="margin">2 Theſ. 3. 4.</note> That they may be aſhamed. And<note n="(3)" place="margin">2 Cor. 10. 8. 1 Cor. 5. 6. 1 Tim. 5. 20.</note> to bring them to repentance. So in regard of the Church; that it may appear ſhe maintains no vile perſons; that other members may be free from infection, and that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may fear. In <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 12. there is a double duty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, To mark, To avoid. The parties to be avoided are deſcribed from the effects, Diviſions and Offences; they who cauſe theſe are to be marked, avoided. The rule to which they are contrary, the doctrine they had heard, namely of Salvation, of Chriſt, which they had learned in that Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, or their firſt Converters. Falſe teachers then are to be marked, ſo that we be not deceived by them, they cauſing Diviſions and Offences. A watchful eye is to be upon all ſuch<note place="margin">Mat. 7. 14, 15. Phil. 3. 2.</note> who by their opinions or life cauſe diviſions contrary to the doctrine of ſalvation. Diviſions and Scandals ſtriking at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eart of Religion, and of the Church. The Apoſtles rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to avoid ſuch, are, The one Negative, <hi>q. d.</hi> you think they ſerve Chriſt, but they do not, not ſubmitting to his will, not ſeeking to pleaſe him in all things. The other Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative, they ſerve their own bellies, themſelves, their own turns, their profit, eaſe, maintenance, vain glory, ambition, carnal affections, they aiming at their own gain and credit, and not the glory of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                        </label> We think they are good and honeſt men, and their wayes good, they being ſo ſucceſsful, they multiplying ſo much.</head>
                     <p n="1">
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> 1. For their goodneſs and honeſty I will give you Mr. <hi>Hodges</hi> anſwers in a Sermon upon 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 2. before the Houſe of Commons, <hi>March</hi> 10. 1646. You hear (ſaith he) what the Apoſtle ſayes, That many have a form, and yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the power of godlineſs, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 5. The Wolf in the Fable, that he might not be ſuſpected, but the more eaſily make his prey of the ſilly ſheep, put on a skin of theirs, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:41930:11"/> 2. Why (ſaith he) ſhould you think to ſay, he is an honeſt<note place="margin">Pag. 58.</note> or a pious man ſhould be a fooliſh plea in caſe of abuſing coyn, theft, treaſon or the like; and yet ſhould be of weight and force in this far greater buſineſs, and more horrid miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief?</p>
                     <p n="2">2. For their increaſing, it is no argument of goodneſs.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The <hi>Arrians</hi> did ſo overſpread the Church, that it was<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Miratur mundus ſe factum eſſe Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, St.</hi> Hierom.</note> a ſaying <hi>Athanaſius</hi> againſt the World (namely of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) and the World againſt <hi>Athanaſius.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. Popery did ſpread ſo faſt and far, that Papiſts tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphingly ſaid and do, Where was your Church before <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi> and they make univerſality a note of the Church.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Mahumetaniſm</hi> is ſo ſpread not only over the <hi>Turks</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Fox,</hi> tom. 2. p. 993. See <hi>Breer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woods</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry of Languages and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions.</note> which are large, and many in <hi>Europe, Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africk,</hi> but in other Kingdoms and Countreys which are not under the <hi>Turk,</hi> it having ſpread over <hi>Perſia, India, China, Tarta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mahomet</hi> aroſe about ſix hundred years after Chriſt, yet he hath bewitched ſo great a part of the World, although his Alcaron contains ſuch abſurdities, which are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be laught at then named.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                        </label> But what need you to trouble us with ſuch like things, we being free from the one and the other.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> We living where and when errors do abound (for we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not all be in the truth holding contraries) it is very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Mr. <hi>Paget</hi> names about 143. errors and hereſies which lately ſprung up and ſhewed themſelves, not naming the <hi>Quakers,</hi> of whom there was no notice when he did write that Book. Among this ſwarm he names Papiſts, praying in an unknown tongue, holding Tranſubſtantiation, Purgatory, &amp;c. Familiſts blaſphemouſly affirming they are Godified with God, Anabaptiſts affirming Baptiſm to be the mark of the Beaſt, from Antichriſt. <hi>Antinomians</hi> teaching no Law, no ſorrow, ſuch an eaſie way to heaven, that many follow them (concerning whom Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſaith, I do not ſit down in<note place="margin">Pref. to Inf. Chur. memb.</note> an <hi>Antinomian</hi> conceit, that I have nothing to do but expreſs my joy and thankfulneſs) Independents pretending to have a model of Government revealed to them, better than all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41930:11"/> Churches. Sabbatarians affirming the Jewiſh Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath is to be kept. Anti-Sabbatarians teaching there is no Sabbath, every day being a Sabbath to Chriſtians. <hi>Thraskites</hi> obſerving many Jewiſh Ceremonies. <hi>Millenaries</hi> believing that Chriſt ſhall reign a thouſand years on the earth. <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> teaching that Chriſt did not ſatisfie for ſins. <hi>Arrians</hi> denying Chriſt's Deity. Soul-ſleepers, Divorcers and others. He dedicates his Book to the Lord Major, and ſome chief Citizens of <hi>London.</hi> He tells them that he had lived almoſt fifty years amongſt them. He commends their care againſt the infection of the Plague; he minds them that the plague of Hereſie is greater; he ſhews how <hi>Antioch</hi> was conſumed, being a Nurſery of Hereticks; how <hi>Nicomedia</hi> a meeting place for <hi>Arrians</hi> was ſwallowed up; how the Anabaptiſts meeting in Conventicles ſurprized <hi>Munſter;</hi> and how hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Amſterdam</hi> eſcaped them. Then he gives from Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> he from St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> notes of them: They are great boaſters of their own worth and actions, as <hi>Simon Magus</hi> and the <hi>Gn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſticks.</hi> They are blown up with pride, which drives ſome to <hi>Rome,</hi> ſome to <hi>Amſterd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m.</hi> They are deceitful, ſlanderers, Separatiſts, in this equalling the Jeſuits. They are treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly ſeditious, not preaching peace, but diviſion. They have a ſhew of auſterity and holineſs. Then he ſhews the end of his writing to be to give warning to well-meaning people to avoid errors, fore-warning them to this end to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of private Conventicles, and to keep cloſe to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of the Word, and Communion of Saints in the Church.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſaith, there are Devils abroad in the ſhape of Angels of light, and Wolves within, as ſheep without.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Mr. <hi>Vines</hi> in his faſt Sermon before the Houſe of Commons, <hi>March</hi> 10. 1646. ſaith, Are not the errors which are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ife amongſt us, either by infecting perſons of place and quality, grown into that boldneſs? or by carrying away <hi>Barnabas</hi> alſo crept into that credit? or by ſpreading far and wide riſen to that ſtrength? that they do face, if not ſeem able to put into danger of routing our common ſaith, publick worſhip, authorized Miniſtry, long and much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41930:12"/> &amp; promiſed reformation. This to the common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my is the Cape of good Hope; the ſound part are afraid leſt the truth ſhould come to beg for poor quarter, and be led captive, following the chariot of triumphing liberty.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Mr. <hi>Hodges</hi> in his faſt Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mon at the ſame time and place, ſaith, How ſad a ſight is it to behold the ſpreading of this infection, the ſhoals that being perverted follow theſe pernicious wayes? to ſee how faſt theſe tares thrive, this leaven ſpreads, this gangrene frets? The Kingdom looks like a lazar houſe or field fought in many places; by reaſon of this, how many are there of all ages inſnared by them? The hoary head that is ready to deſcend to the grave, and your hopeful ſpring that ſeemed to promiſe life and happineſs to the Church and State. And in his Epiſtle he ſaith, The Prince of flies hath raiſed ſuch ſwarms of flies in every cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of our Land, that many of our Congregations and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies are miſerably fly-blown with hereſie and corrupt tenets. Alſo in his Sermon he hath this paſſage. Did ever former ages produce more hideous monſters than we have riſen up amongſt us in this poor Iſland? Are there not <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> who<hi>—Valen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>inians,</hi> who<hi>—Gnoſticks,</hi> who—The <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans</hi> opinions. The <hi>Corinthians</hi> form, the <hi>Carpocratians</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probity, and the Chriſtians profeſſion.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Mr. <hi>Bayly</hi> hath diſcovered and numbred ſwarms of errors and hereſies amongſt us, and ſaith that the greateſt hazard of the Church this day comes from the evil of errors,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 17 2 Pet. 2. 1, 2.</note> it eating up the ſoul as a gangrene the body, and bringing deſtruction.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. The Parliament which was 1646. were ſo ſenſible hereof, that they appointed a Faſt to be kept, <hi>March</hi> 10. for the ſuppreſſing and preventing of the growth and ſpreading<note place="margin">2 Pet 2. 1. 2 Pet. 2. 2.</note> of Hereſies and Blaſphemies, the forenamed Mr. <hi>Vines</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hodges</hi> preached before the Houſe of Commons, their Text in the Margent.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Mr. <hi>Edw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rds</hi> hath Book after Book to this purpoſe, diſcovering the ſwarms of groſs errors maintained in our times, to the number of above an hundred and ſeventy. He g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ves us a Catalogue of their many blaſphemies, of ſtrange
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41930:12"/> paſſages in their prayers, and then parallels them with the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> in St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> time. The <hi>Donatiſts</hi> complained of perſecution, ſo do theſe. The <hi>Donatiſts</hi> were violent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe who oppoſed their way, ſo are theſe. <hi>Donatists</hi> were great flatterers, extolling their parties for gifts and abilities, ſo do theſe. <hi>Donatiſts</hi> condemned that in others, they practiſed themſelves, ſo do theſe. <hi>Donatiſts</hi> were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to have their writings examined by judicious men, but kept them in the dark; becauſe they cannot agree toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or amongſt themſelves, becauſe they know not how long they ſhall be of one mind, and how far they ſhall go, becauſe they would not offend their own party, and becauſe they would not diſcover their own weakneſs, ſo theſe. The <hi>Donatiſts</hi> did much wrong to Authors, miſquoting them, ſo do theſe.</p>
                     <p>He parallels them with Jeſuits, affirming that Separatiſts and Jeſuits agree ſo, that both ſend out emiſſaries to ſpread their errors; both uſe pious frauds to propagate their cauſe, both infinuate into great mens houſes, both are full of equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, ſaying one thing, meaning another; both are active, reſtleſs ſpirits, never without plenty and fine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns; both work by inſtruments unſuſpected, getting their work done by others; both will run great hazards, being daring to effect their ends.</p>
                     <p>He parallels them with divers others, amongſt whom, with <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate; as <hi>Julian</hi> was a ſcoffer of Chriſt, of Chriſtians, of Scriptures; ſo ſome Sectaries of Chriſt, ſome of the Trinity, ſome of the Miniſtry, ſome of the O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dinances. <hi>Julian</hi> was a great enemy to learning, ſo theſe. He was a Patron of toleration, which theſe ſeek for.</p>
                     <p>Then he ſets down 28 of their evil practiſes, of which theſe are ſome. They aſcribe all good done, to be by their party. They call themſelves the godly, and well affected. They pretend one thing, and mind another. They ſtrive to have the Church without Miniſters. They would have no Church Government, or if any with a toleration. Some of them put down all ſinging of Pſalms, and keep on their hats at prayer. Some of them pretend to miracles, viſions, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41930:13"/> for their way to confirm their Doctrines. When Books come out confuting them, they tell the people they are or ſhall be confuted, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nſwered to delude the people. Some of them have ſtrangly abuſed Bapt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſm, dreſſing a Cat, and in ſcorn and contempt of the Ordinance baptized it. When they print, they give their Books glorious titles, as Innocency and truth triumphing, The ſtorming of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, &amp;c. They will ſeem to be what they are not, until they have ſerved their turn, waiting opportunity to make void all they ſeemed to grant. They are reſtleſs to promote their cauſe, obſerving all tempers and humours. They deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately judge of the eſtates and actions of all men who are not for them, unſainting them as fallen from grace. They walk more looſly and at large over what they did before they turned Sectaries, and in compariſon of Presbyterians, doing<note place="margin">He was one.</note> many things under the name of Chriſtian liberty, which Profeſſors formerly did not, nor durſt do; when they have ſet to their hands to many things, they have deſired to ſee the papers, and would not reſtore them. They upbraid Presbyterians for former conformity, as time-ſervers, to make people believe the Presbyterians are not conſcienci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, only time-ſervers, whereas theſe were Conformiſts, forward Epiſcopal men, thruſting others out, who would not be ſo, naming ſeven; yea, ſome of the chief of them went further in conformity then Presbyterians, naming three. Thus he. Although the words of theſe men ſhew abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſwarming of errors, yet they forget that ſome of themſelves, and of their party were the parents of theſe ſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious births, by oppoſing and deſtroying the worſhip of God, and Government of the Church, which whilſt vigorous, did curb and ſuppreſs them with good ſucceſs.</p>
                     <p>We living therefore when and where errors abound, I deſire you not to take it ill that I uſe mine endeavour, that neither you nor I may live or die in error, and as beloved brethren to deſire you not to err. I am a man therefore ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to err, but ſuch a one who deſire not to live in any er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, but erring to be reformed. And ſince you and I do err in ſomethings, being ſo contrary in our opinions, I will ſhew
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41930:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> you my grounds, perſwading me that I am in the right, and that it is you, not I that do err. And in doing this I aim at no mans prejudice. I ſhall ſhew no paſſion; although I have been chollerick and paſſionate, yet I have been ſo long a Scholar in Chriſts School, as to know my ſelf, my duty, and not to be overſwayed by ſuch corruptions. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you therefore in meekneſs, in cool blood, as you and I ſhall anſwer at the great day, the great Judge of the world, to conſider conſcientiouſly a few following particulars.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="ground">
                     <head>The Firſt.</head>
                     <p>I did and do think, I was and am ſtill perſwaded, that the taking up of arms lately amongſt us, as for King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (but indeed againſt the K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ng) was unlawful, and a rebellion to be repented of. As many others, ſo ſome of you did, and perhaps ſtill think otherwiſe, one of us muſt needs be guilty of a groſs and grievous error. I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that I in this err not, ſince as I judge, we may not take up arms againſt a lawful Soveraign, ſhould he be vile, wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, unjuſt, an Idolater; and that ours againſt whom arms were taken, was neither. My grounds are, 1. The ſacred Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures,<note place="margin">Exod. 22. 28. Gal. 10 20 Rom. 13. 1, 2, 3. 1 Pet. 2. 13.</note> which teach me that we muſt hold our tongues, much more our hands; yea, and that we muſt take heed to our thoughts, and that they are not to be reſiſted, becauſe they are God's Ordinance; and ſo a reſiſting of them is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of God. I know they are called the Ordinance of man; and ſo they are ſubjectively, the power being exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by man; objectively, being about the ſociety of man; finally, becauſe for the ſingular good of man; and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally, they may be of man in places where they are ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive; yet is the power Gods, originally they are of God, who appoints that ſome ſhould govern, ſome obey, and it is the Lord who maintains and upholds this Order. I know that ſome cavilling, are ready to ſay, As ſome ſuch are good, ſo ſome are bad; and are bad ones of God? or how can bad ones be of God? not conſidering that God gives the Kingdom of heaven only to the good, but the Kingdoms of the earth to good and bad; and that the power of the bad is of God, and to be obeyed, although the abuſe of the power
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41930:14"/> where it is abuſed, is of themſelves. Their power therefore cauſally is from God, his Ordinance, they are Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and reſiſters reſiſt O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dinances, ſo him.</p>
                     <p>Alſo becauſe ſuch who reſiſt are to receive greater loſs than of goods, than of life it ſelf, even damnation. I have ſeen ſome anſwers to Dr. <hi>Fearn.</hi> The reaſons of ſome to juſtifie their taking up of arms, (I have them by me) and the Anticaveliariſm to that purpoſe, being willing to ſee what could be ſaid; and their Arguments to juſtifie their doings, that I might joyn, if the courſe was warrantable. But alas, I found much ſaid, little proved, from Scripture. The peoples reſcuing <hi>Jonathan</hi> is pleaded; whereas it is cleer that the<note place="margin">1 Sam. 14. 44, 45.</note> people drew not into arms of themſelves, but at <hi>Sauls</hi> command; and by a loving importunity they did hinder the execution of a paſſionate unlawful command. Here no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is to be found but loyalty. <hi>Davids</hi> being againſt <hi>Saul</hi> is to as little purpoſe. <hi>David</hi> never reſiſted, he alwayes fled<note place="margin">1 Sam. 24. 1 Sam. 26.</note> from place to place, he was never found fighting, reſiſting, nor hurting, no not when <hi>Saul</hi> was in his hands. Nor doth the Prophets wiſhing thoſe with him to hold the meſſenger, prove that Kings Officers, therefore themſelves may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted;<note place="margin">2 King. 6. 32.</note> for it is one thing to hold a meſſenger faſt, another to ſtrike, to ſlay. The holding is a delaying of the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the other ſhews contempt of the power. But <hi>Eliſha,</hi> who knew of the meſſengers coming knew alſo that the King was ſorry for that command, and was coming to withſtand it, as the Text expreſly hath it. He in ſo doing did the Kings will; as if he had ſaid, Hold him but a while, until the King come, who will have no ſuch thing done. Beſides, it might be ſaid, that all the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the ten Tribes, were themſelves but rebels againſt the hauſe of <hi>David.</hi> We never read in Scripture that good people did take up arms<note place="margin">2 Chron. 33. 5, &amp;c.</note> againſt their Kings, when bad as <hi>Saul, Manaſſes;</hi> nor that the Prophets ever perſwaded them againſt ſuch; and it ſhews heavy judgments againſt thoſe who have rebelled againſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven bad Kings, as <hi>Amnon</hi> and others.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. My ſecond ground is this. Reſiſting of Kings is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the doctrine and practiſe of the primitive times, of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41930:14"/> the ancient Fathers, Martyrs, and other holy men, until of late the Jeſuits began to flouriſh, who turned Religion into policy; and ſome diſorderly reformers, as alſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain eminent of the Presbyterians, as <hi>Grotius,</hi> who wrote a Book <hi>de jure belli &amp; pacis,</hi> which did much hurt in theſe late times, but it is well anſwered in a Treatiſe, called, Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations concerning the Original of Government; ſo few miſled, have defended (and weakly) reſiſtance, that Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> in his <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> could find but two Engliſh Divines leaning that way, when he wrote his Book, which is not long. And all along the primitive times, they were for obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and againſt reſiſtance, even of perſecutors; as <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>
                        <note place="margin">See for the Judgment of Antiquity in this point, that excellent Book of the Lord Primate of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Dr. <hi>Uſher,</hi> entituled, The power of the Prince, and obedience of Subjects; publiſhed with a learned Preface, by Dr. <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
                        </note> to <hi>Antonius</hi> the Emperor, <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch, Athena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> in his Apology to <hi>Aurelius</hi> do ſhew. <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy writes to this purpoſe; In one night with a few fire-brands we could be revenged, we want not number of men nor arms; your houſes, your Countreys are full of us; and we who take Martyrdom ſo gladly, were we fewer, what were we not able to do, if it was more lawful by our Relig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on to ſlay than be ſlain; yea, we could leave you, and ſo your places deſolate, and ſubject to enemies. To this purpoſe he. To this I will add. There was a Legion called the <hi>Theban</hi> Legion, conſiſting of 6666 valiant Chriſtian Soldiers, for refuſing to commit idolatry, every tenth man was executed. One <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritius</hi> taking the reſt aſide, encouraged them from Scripture to ſuffer, not to reſiſt; they were decimated and executed the ſecond time: Then <hi>Exuperius</hi> taking into his hands the Enſigns of the Legion, ſaid, to theſe arms I provoke you not, but to ſuffer. And to the Emperor, We are thy Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, but Gods ſervants; we owe thee our imployment, to him our innocency; we have our weapons, yet reſiſt not, being willing to die innocent, rather than to live Traitors, our weapons we caſt away; ſo they were all ſlain, not one reſiſting. And all our ſtrict Divines, until our ſad
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41930:15"/> reſiſtance (Dr. <hi>Owens</hi> two excepted) as Mr. <hi>Dod,</hi> on Com. 5. Dr. <hi>Tayler</hi> on <hi>Titus,</hi> Mr. <hi>Byfield</hi> on <hi>Peter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Parre</hi> on <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> and others were againſt reſiſtance.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. My third ground. I found reſiſtance to be againſt the<note place="margin">Judge <hi>Jenkins.</hi>
                        </note> Laws of our Nation, which tell us, That to ſeize the Kings For<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s and Magazines, is high Treaſon; ſo to remove his Councellors by arms; likewiſe to levy War to alter Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; to levy War to alter the Law; to counterfeit the great Seal; to adhere to any State in the Kingdom, but the Kings Majeſty; ſo to impriſon the King until he agree to demands: to impriſon the King, to deſtroy him, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the King, by the Law are high Treaſons.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. A fourth thing which confirmed me, were the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of ſome men, as Dr. <hi>Fearn,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Symons,</hi> who ſuffered loſs of what was dear to him, rather than take up arms againſt the King, ſhewing twelve reaſons why he durſt not joyn in that way. The ſum in brief take thus. 1. Then he ſhould aſſiſt in many evils. 2. The way was not of God. 3. It deſtroys the whole Law of God, breaking all the ten Commandements, ſhewing how, every one particularly. 4. It is inconſiſtent with the Goſpel. 5. It contradicts the practiſe of Chriſtianity. 6. It is oppoſite to the calling of Miniſters. 7. It is contrary to common prudence to go in ſuſpected ways. 8. It diſſents from the Rules of Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to fight againſt him who ſo long preſerved us. 9. It is againſt nature it ſelf, to conſent to our own deſtruction. 10. It is againſt reaſon to go in a way in which all who are gone before us have periſhed. 11. It is againſt our Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy. 12. And it brings in and ſets up Popery, and Popiſh doctrine. For example, 1. The doctrine of reſiſting Kings is Popery. 2. To place infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of judgment in man, as the Papiſts in the Pope. Theſe in the Parliament. 3. Papiſts believe in the creature, the Church. Theſe in the Parliament. 4. Papiſts ſay faith is not to be kept with Hereticks. Theſe with Malignants. 5. Papiſts believe it to be meritorious to die in their holy War, as they call it. Theſe believe the ſame of thoſe who die for the cauſe. 6. Both conſent in the doctrines of pious
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41930:15"/> frauds. 7. Papiſts preſs the precepts of men. Theſe the Ordinances of Parliament. 8. Papiſts would have all to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Pope. Theſe to the Parliament. 9. Both agree in violence and cruelty; in his hearing (he ſaith) he heard one ſay, It was good to aſſiſt the Parliament way; for if the King prevailed we ſhould find favour, if they prevail, we ſhall have cruelty. 10. Both have the ſpirit of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, cauſing men to deny the truth they had learned and profeſſed. 11. And in the point of defamation they are as dexterous as Papiſts, for upon a ſudden they can do that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a godly Miniſter, which the Devil in many years was not able to do, making him ſeem ſcandalous, ſo odious. Thus he. I know what is pleaded for reſiſtance, and taking up of arms; namely,</p>
                     <div n="1" type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1</label> If ſubjects may not reſiſt, then they muſt obey unlawful commands contrary to <hi>Act. 5. 29.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> Active obedience is to be given to their lawful commands; Paſſive, when they command things unlawful: So we are<note place="margin">Dan. 3. 17. 6. 7.</note> alwayes to obey, by executing their will actively, or by ſubmitting to the puniſhment paſſively. If an Emperor be a <hi>Nero</hi> or <hi>Caligula,</hi> what warrant then to take up arms againſt ſuch a King againſt whom envy it ſelf could not faſten any aſperſions?</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> They ſaid they took not up arms againſt the King, but againſt his evil Councellors.</head>
                        <p>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> This is a new coyn'd diſtinction to cover the ugly face of rebellion. And it is a vain diſtinction, for to oppoſe his Councellors is to oppoſe him. And it is certain Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours are not to be reſiſted. But why then were not theſe<note place="margin">1 P<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 1. 2.: 3</note> evil men named? why not demanded that they might be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally puniſhed? Why? The ſequel ſhew'd it was againſt the King himſelf.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <hi>John Blackleach</hi> in his endeavours, Printed 1650. juſtifieth <hi>John Goodwin</hi> for juſtifying the murder of the King, Pag. 53. and pag. 54. he affirms, that they did not take away the life of the King, but of one that had been King, and hoped ſo to have been again. And <hi>G. W.</hi> in his <hi>Reſp. Anglic.</hi> pag. 32. ſaith, That the Parliament finding him (the King)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41930:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> the evil Councellor, a ſettled and obſtinate Tyrant. And pag. 41. for a Parliament and State to call a Tyrant to an account, is not unlawful.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>3</label> That they did was in obedience to publick command.</head>
                        <p>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> Obedience is due, and to be yielded to authority; but then the Authority muſt be lawful, not like <hi>Sheba</hi>'s. And<note place="margin">2 Sam. 20. 12.</note> the thing commanded lawful. They had neither, who reſiſted the King.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>4</label> If ſubjects may not reſiſt, then it ſeems Kings may do what they will.</head>
                        <p>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> Shall we reject the Word of God for ſeeming inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences? God commands us to obey, and ſhall we pretend inconveniences? Beſides, Kings are not at ſuch liberty, but accountable to God. And ſubjects have many remedies, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations, diſſwaſives, and reproofs, by their <hi>Nathans</hi> to their <hi>Davids,</hi> prayer, flight.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>5</label> But if Kings command to worſhip Devils, ſhould we not reſiſt? ſhould we obey?</head>
                        <p>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> Devil-worſhip was commanded by Emperors, yet Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans took up no arms for the matter, they betook themſelves<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 20. 1 Pet. 4. 12, 13.</note> to prayers, and patient ſuffering, according to Scripture.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>6</label> But what if the Government is in danger by evil managing?</head>
                        <p>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> We are enjoyned obedience upon a great penalty; let us in obedience perform our part, and leave the ordering of all to God; there coming many and greater inconveniences by<note place="margin">Rom. 13. 5</note> taking liberty to reſiſt, making inferiors to over-rule their ſuperiors, the ſubjects their Prince. Nor can there be great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er inconveniences in a family, or a Kingdom, than when there is no obedience but to what ſeems good in mens own eyes. Our Saviour ſhews what follows the dividing of a Kingdom againſt it ſelf. The ſelf of a Common-wealth is the<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>k 3. 21</note> Law thereof (the common ſurety between Governour and governed.) The ſelf of a Kingdom is the Religion of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. The ſelf of a Church is doctrine and diſcipline, the one as the Corn, the other as the Hedge, which like body and ſoul muſt not be divided. Reſiſting lawful Authority in law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful things, makes ſuch diviſions, brings ſtrange inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. I will conclude this, propounding five things to your conſiderations.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <pb n="25" facs="tcp:41930:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> 1. That the ſame God who commands children and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to obey in all things (which are lawful) their Parents and Maſters, commands ſubjects in all lawful things to obey Kings, if not more, ſince ſuch may command both us and ours, both Parents and Children. An houſhold is a little Common-wealth; and a Common-wealth is a great houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold. Governours of houſes may and do expect obedience from their inferiors; ſo Magiſtrates from them. We are to do as we would be done by.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. That Chriſtian obedience doth greatly adorn the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel<note place="margin">Tit. 2 5, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>0 1 Pet. 2. 15, 16.</note> of Chriſt; and by it we do profeſs an acknowledgment of Gods Ordinance.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. That we have a great advantage by Government, by<note place="margin">Rom. 13 4</note> Governours, they are for our good; whereas Anarchy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens a window to confuſion. Government is for our good natural, that our life and ſafety may be preſerved; for our<note place="margin">Mr. Parre.</note> good moral, that we may be brought from vice to vertue; for our good civil, that we may enjoy poſſeſſions, and that publick honeſty may be defended; and for our ſpiritual good, having God's worſhip eſtabliſhed. Some perhaps ſay good men are moleſted. But let ſuch know, that good Magiſtrates are good mens nouriſhers; bad are their tryers, ſo for their good. And if any good men are puniſhed for good, it comes from the abuſe of the power. However it is certain, Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience<note place="margin">Rom. 13. 3</note> brings praiſe, is a doing of good, and is a good work in an high degree, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 1, 2. As if the Apoſtle ſhould ſay no good work can be expected from him, who obeyeth not the Rulers, diſobedience to ſuch being an high breach of the ſecond Table.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. That great danger hangs over the heads of reſiſters. A cruel meſſenger, calamity, ruin, damnation; not to obey<note place="margin">Prov. 17. 11. 24. 21. Rom. 13. 2</note> is reſiſting, and fighting againſt God. The murmurings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> were againſt God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 8. <hi>Hab.</hi> 16. 11.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. That it is the brand and badge of filthy dreamers, and ſeparating ſeducers to deſpiſe dominions, and to ſpeak evil of dignities, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 18. <hi>Jude</hi> 8.</p>
                        <p>I can ſhew you Books to incourage you in that way, but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41930:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> in them all, not one convincing Scripture; no Law of the Land, nor practiſe of the Orthodox Chriſtians, who lived in the pureſt primitive times; for all theſe are oppoſite to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance. If therefore in this any of you do ſtill err, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what you have done, repent for the ſame, that God may pardon you, as the King hath done. And that men may not think or ſay, you would act over the former Tragedy again had you but opportunity.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="ground">
                     <head>The ſecond.</head>
                     <p>In the year of our Lord, 1661. I printed a little Book con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining three ſhort Treatiſes, one of the right of Kings, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Scripture, A defence of Pſalm-ſinging, And an Eſſay for orderly hearing; you have them amongſt you. That Eſſay ſhews that I or ſome of you do greatly &amp; grievouſly err; ſome in going elſewhere ordinarily to hear the Word, having it of you preached at home in your Church; or I in not ſhewing that thoſe who do ſo (and I think I do ſufficiently prove it) by ſo doing, are guilty of ſin upon ſin. As of ſin againſt God three wayes: Againſt the Church, and Commonwealth, and Laws of both. Againſt their own Paſtor four wayes. Againſt the Miniſter they go to hear four wayes. Againſt the day two wayes. Againſt their common neighbour two wayes. Againſt their Chriſtian brethren two wayes. Againſt thoſe who dwell in places where preaching is not two wayes. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelves four wayes. Againſt their families three wayes. And againſt the rules of Chriſtianity four wayes. I beſeech you in cold blood to conſider, That things of this nature are not matters to be dallied with. If therefore I do not err, the doing of ſome of you is groſsly evil, and noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly ſinful, you add and heap ſin to ſin, ſubmit therefore to the truth maintained. And if your ſo well improved and rarely gifted teachers can confute thoſe reaſons, and ſo ſhew that I do err, you ſhall find me willing to alter my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                     <div type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                           </label> 
                           <hi>You perhaps think and ſay I preach unprofitably, one of your articles againſt me formerly being thus: He hath preached ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitably, that three or fourſcore of his Pariſhioners have been forced to go into the Countrey to hear others. And he hath forced</hi>
                           <pb n="27" facs="tcp:41930:17"/> 
                           <hi>ſome to remove their habitations becauſe they could not profit by</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Not one.</note> 
                           <hi>him. Thus your Article. And when a Committee-man told ſome of you, that I was eſteemed by the Countrey a painful Preacher, he was anſwered, To little purp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſe.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p n="1">
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> 1. I confeſs I then had preached unprofitably in regard of my ſelf, for by mears of my preaching and practiſe, I loſt both goods and Living.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. In regard of your cauſe I alſo preached unprofitably, not furthering, but hindering of it. This being another of your Articles. He hath diſſwaded thoſe who have been wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to lend money, and to put in horſes, and to bear arms for King and Parliament, bringing in proofs of Scripture, and urging the practiſe of the primitive times, to pervert the judgment of his Hearers, and to perſwade them rather to ſuffer than take up arms for the Parliament.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. If in reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rd of ſanctification and ſalvation, the leſs profitable my preaching was, the more is my grief, and the more your ſin and ſhame. Either I and hundreds more did then err in being of a contrary opinion, or you in ſo articling then, or thinking ſo now, ſome abſenting themſelves wholly, ſome often. Had I preached only here, ſuch words and doings would have made me afraid and aſhamed to come into a Pulpit. But before I came hither to dwell at firſt, I being accounted a Preacher both here and elſewhere, and after my ſettling here adjudged ſo by many, and thoſe judicious, as their frequent coming hither, and to other places where I preached did ſhew, until our unhappy diviſions. But when I would not leave praying for Biſhops as deſired, when I would not freely contribute to War as requeſted, nor pay Taxes to foment War, as enjoyned; when I refuſed to preach up Wars and fighting, and ſtir'd up people to pray for the peace of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> then, and not until then I was an unprofitable Preacher, unfit to preach, yea to live amongſt you, and continue here. And bleſſed be God, and I heartily thank you for that kindneſs in driving me away, for had I continued, your doings would have made me poor, yea more, my life uncomfortable; and worſt of all, my repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation wholly loſt, reporting me a Malignant, a Delinquent,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41930:18"/> one rotten at the heart, a no, or an unprofitable Preacher; yea ſuch, that it was ſaid to a Parliament man, a friend, If your Worſhip knew him as well as we, you would not take his part. And in all places where I came in the troubles, even from ſuch who were contrary minded to me, and of your way and judgment, I found love to my ſelf, and ſuch liking to my preaching (the ſame Sermons I preached here) that I was importuned by many, to many places in City and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. And ſuch approbation there was of my preaching, that I (and others in my condition) being ſilenced, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Clergy, Committee, and ſome great ones of that way obtained for me freedom and liberty to preach, having forborn but five weeks; yea ſuch approbation hath been given to my preaching, and to the profitableneſs of it, by multitudes of people, no whit inferior to you, nor in no kind; that I bleſs God I neither then feared, nor now do fear to come into a Pulpit.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. If you err, thinking ſtill (as it ſeems you do) my preaching to be unprofitable, I deſire you to ſee whether the fault is in my preaching, or in your ſelves. I hope you will acknowledge <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to be a profitable Preacher; his Hearers it appears did not, he complaining, <hi>Who hath believed our report?</hi> You have I believe the ſame thoughts of <hi>Jeremiah</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Iſa. 53. 1.</note> and <hi>Ezekel;</hi> their hearers had not, <hi>Jeremiah's</hi> telling him he preached falſely, and that they would not do according to<note place="margin">Jer. 43. 2. 44. 16, 17. Ezek. 33. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.</note> what he had ſpoken. And <hi>Ezekiels</hi> not at all edifying by him, although they delighted to hear him. Surely you will yield Chriſt to be a profitable Preacher, yet many of his Hearers ſo far from judging ſo, that they wholly left him; yea, ſo<note place="margin">Joh. 6. 66. Joh. 6. 67.</note> many, that he ſaid to ſome of his followers, <hi>Will you alſo go away?</hi> Was the fault in the Preacher, or in the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> when one was for <hi>Paul,</hi> another for <hi>Apollo,</hi> another for <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas?</hi>
                           <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 1, 2.</note> Was the blame in the Preacher or Hearers, when they would not endure ſound doctrine, but after their own luſts did heap to themſelves Teachers having itching ears, turning away their ears from the truth, being turned to Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles?<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 3, 4.</note> Was the fault in Manna (that heavenly food) or in the men (a murmuring generation) when it was loathed?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41930:18"/> Let people hear without prejudice, with better affections, and more preparation, and then ſee if the Word is unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. But if the many hundreds (as well as I) who by word and hand have approved of me, and of my preaching as not unprofitable, if we all do err, that I am ſo unprofitable at <hi>Broughton</hi> (I deſiring your good and profiting) I can God permitting me, and perhaps will make tryal whether ſome other can profit you, being aſſured that I can preach in many places where my preaching will be eſteemed acceptable and profitable.</p>
                        <p n="6">6. But take heed to your ſelves; for if we be but the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of death, we do our Maſters work, we do what we are ſent for. And if we cannot give our account with joy, but<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 15. Heb. 13. 17.</note> with grief, I am ſure that will be unprofitable to you. I had thoughts not once to mention ſuch things, not to ſhew one diſliking word or look to ſuch who endeavoured to ruin me and mine; but to prevent greater inconveniences into which I ſee ſome running, imitating St. <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> I play the fool in his ſenſe.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="ground">
                     <head>The Third.</head>
                     <p>A third particular in which you and I much differ, is about perſecution, concerning which, you or I do greatly err; ſome of you complaining of perſecution, and one of your Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles againſt me being thus. He hath been and ſtill is an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to all thoſe that profeſs the power of godlineſs in his Pariſh, and hath perſecuted them as far as poſſibly he could, and eſtranged himſelf from the ſociety of all the faithful and godly Miniſters about us, and upon all occaſions would give reproachful ſpeeches againſt them. Thus your Article. And I think I was perſecuted, and by ſome of you; and as for your ſelves, you yet never knew what it meant. That you or I may come out of this error, let us firſt ſee what perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is.</p>
                     <p>Perſecution is more than affliction; many afflictions have no perſecutions in them, but every act of perſecution hath many afflictions in it. Afflictions many ariſe from irrational, yea from inanimate creatures; perſecution is the act of a<note place="margin">Act. 9 1.</note>
                        <pb n="30" facs="tcp:41930:19"/> rational creature, reaſon abuſed or clouded being the ſpring of perſecution. One wicked man may vex or afflict another to death, but none are ſaid to be perſecuted but the good; evil men are puniſhed, good men perſecuted. And if an evil man is perſecuted, it is becauſe he makes ſhew or profeſſion of goodneſs. Perſecution in a large ſenſe ſignifies to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;<note place="margin">Job 19 22</note> ſtrictly taken it is the actual oppoſition of any man for the cauſe of God, for righteouſneſs ſake, proceeding from an enemy like zeal againſt his perſon or peace; it is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, when the ſpirit of man riſeth up and oppoſeth another; verbal, when men give hard words and uncharitable cenſures; and real, mentioned <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 18. To do thus, or to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute<note place="margin">Act. 9. 5.</note> is exceeding ſinful, it oppoſing another for doing of good, for holding the truth; yea, it is ſuch a ſin as to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Chriſt. And a perſecutor is a great offendor, yea one of the greateſt ſinners. <hi>Paul</hi> confeſſeth h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mſelf to have been a chief offendor, becauſe a great perſecutor. As it is one of the higheſt acts of graces to be perſecuted, ſo it is<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 15.</note> one of the higheſt acts of wickedneſs to perſecute, it oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Chriſt. See therefore whether you or I were perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, or perſecuted; it being a matter of great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, even of ſalvation. I think and affirm that I was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, which I prove from what I ſuffered, from the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how, and the cauſe why. See what I ſuffered, the loſs of four loads of goods, of above ſeventy ſheep, twelve ſwine, and ſix kine driven away at one time. And <hi>Auguſt</hi> the fourth<note place="margin">
                           <hi>July</hi> 15. 1643.</note> following (not full three weeks) the loſs of my living, the gift of it to another, bearing date that day, although the place was ſupplyed by my care, until the uncivil and unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian carriage of ſome of you forced for bearance. I loſt my reputation ſo far as credit would be given to malicious and falſe reports and accuſations, of being a Malignant, an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to the cauſe of God, yea ſuch a one that all the godly in <hi>Broughton</hi> refuſed to hear my preaching, and went to <hi>Northampton</hi> (ſome ſaying nothing) only to make number, and ſo to make me more noted for a vile perſon; and when ſome have ſeemed to compaſſionate my condition, then ſuch baſe back blows; If you knew him as we do, &amp;c. the manner
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41930:19"/> therefore with all the diſgrace and violence that could be. And why all this? for what cauſe? I could tell you what ſome ſaid; I might be quiet if I would do as you did. I could tell you what ſome of your great ones ſaid; I ſhould be quiet if I would take the Covenant. But I neither durſt do as you did, nor take the Covenant. I had taken the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy (and ſo had many of your leading men) I ſaw the Word of God, the Laws of the Land, and the practiſe of the primitive Church againſt you, which made me more willing to ſuffer than ſin, my ſufferings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for righteouſneſs ſake, for doing my duty, I am bold to ſay, and conclude it was I who was perſecuted, and ſome of you were perſecutors.</p>
                     <div type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                           </label> But what can I ſay to your Article?</head>
                        <p>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> Your own conſciences can tell you, that there is not the leaſt truth in it; that it is a fardle forced, full of falſhoods, ſtuft almoſt with as many groſs lyes as words, and thoſe as falſe as ever came from hell. You know in thoſe dayes I was moſt intimate with ſuch, who were ſaid to be perſecuted; you know that before I was forced away, I never moleſted man, woman or child to the value of a farthing; ſurely, then no perſecutor notwithſtanding that lying Article. And ſince my return I complained of one for not coming to the Communion, but proſecuted it not; and if I had, it could be no perſecution, being for diſobedience; and for to reform. Another for tryal of right; both which I may do again, and be no perſecutor. As for your being perſecuted, I as yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knew nor heard that any of you was moleſted, although ſome of you have even dared authority to uſe ſeverity by your raſh indiſcretion.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="ground">
                     <head>The Fourth.</head>
                     <div type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                           </label> Perhaps you will ſay you are threatned for ſuch and ſuch Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; and is not this perſecution of good men?</head>
                        <p n="1">
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> 1. Surely if one is threatned and no more, that afflicts not much.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. But ſuppoſe from threatning it proceeds to acting, ſo that you are puniſhed; then you will do wiſely to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whether the cauſe of ſuffering-will make it perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41930:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> He who is perſecuted takes up Chriſts Croſs and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows him, he ſuffers not as an evil doer. It is ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d to pull up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 15</note> our ſelves ſelf-created Croſſes. It is ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d to bear the Croſs, and not follow Chriſt. If our Croſs is Chriſts, we then ſuffer for the ſame cauſe to bear witneſs to the truth. In the ſame manner patiently, charitably, thankfully, and for the ſame end as Chriſt to take away ſin, ſo we to further mortification, and be ſtir'd to repentance. How loudly do the Papiſts cry out of perſecution when they are puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and do you think juſtly? How do the <hi>Quakers</hi> glory much of their perſecution for Chriſt? yea, and the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> and <hi>Priſcilianiſts</hi> of old have defended their Hereſies to death, which they counted Martyrdom and Perſecution; yea, the moſt of men moleſted for their opinions do the like, all thinking they ſuffer for Chriſt, for righteouſneſs ſake, and ſo conclude they are perſecuted. It is good when we ſuffer to ſee for what it is that we ſuffer; and ſo ſhould it be as you fear or fancy for your Meetings. Then conſider ſeriouſly and conſcionably, whether in ſo doing you do well or ill, or not well; Authority languiſheth where it is not feared. But if you do well, fear no perſecution, Scripture aſſuring us that Rulers are not a terror to good works, (that is, works, the effect for the cauſe) but to evil works. To un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand<note place="margin">Rom. 13. 3, 4.</note> what are good or evil works, we are to know that works are ſo Theologically taken; ſo a good work is that which is done of faith, and of a ſincere mind, for the glory of God; it is ill when not done ſo. The Magiſtrate cannot judge of theſe, becauſe they are inward; but of good or<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Parre.</hi>
                           </note> evil civilly ſo, which are according to or contrary to the Law divine, humane, poſitive, municipal of Kingdoms, Cities and Corporations, whereby the neceſſary diſcipilne of every State is eſtabliſhed. Of theſe he judgeth. Wilt thou not be afraid, do good; namely, obey and reſiſt not. He doth not mean the profeſſion of Chriſtianity, for that was then hated; but ſuch good which was ſo in the judgment of the Heathen, a civil, honeſt converſation agreeable to the Laws of the State wherein they lived. Then he is the Miniſter of God, for ſuch mens good. But if thou do evil, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. namely, moral
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41930:20"/> or civil evil, contrary to the Decalogue or poſitive Law of the place where thou liveſt, fear; for he beareth not the ſword in vain, ſince we muſt be ſubject, and their Laws obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not only for wrath. 1. Of God who is angry with ſuch who reſiſt Authority. 2. But alſo of the Magiſtrate whom we provoke by diſobedience juſtly to puniſh; but alſo for conſcience ſake; namely, conſcience of our brother, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an offence to a peaceable and loyal ſubject to ſee any to take liberty to break the Laws of the Magiſtrates; as of our ſelves, leſt we wound our own conſciences, every ſoul being bound in conſcience to obey his lawful Magiſtrates; every part of Gods Law binds conſcience. And to obey Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates is part of Gods Law. As we are to render to all theirs, ſo to <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due; to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things which are <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars.</hi> Well, what ſaith the Magiſtrate? what ſaith the Law?<note place="margin">Mat 22. 21</note> Do they allow of your Meetings? Give me leave to tell you how St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> commends a Law Imperial made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Donatists,</hi> and Schiſmaticks in his time, which was, That they who ſeparated from the Church, and had pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Conventicles, ſhould be puniſhed with pecuniary mulcts, their Leaders with baniſhment, the place wherein they met to be forfeited to the Emperor; they ſhould have no power to beſtow their own Goods by will, nor enjoy any Legacy bequeathed to them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                           </label> But you perhaps will ſay, If there is any Law againſt ſuch Meetings, it is not good.</head>
                        <p n="1">
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> 1. Will not Papiſts, <hi>Quakers,</hi> and who not, object the ſame of Laws made againſt them?</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Is it tollerable that a Statute made upon long delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, by ſo many wiſe men, and ſuch in Authority, ſhould be diſclaimed for the private opinions of ſome novel Divines and unletter'd perſons?</p>
                        <p n="3">3. We ſhould be modeſt, and not think our ſelves wiſer than we are, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 3.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. A good ſubject examines not what is beſt, but what is commanded, and ſubmits to it, it being lawful.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. If in making Laws every mans fancy was to be regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there would be no end nor order.</p>
                        <p n="6">
                           <pb n="34" facs="tcp:41930:21"/> 6. If men doubt of the lawfulneſs of things commanded, let them go for reſolution to ſuch who are peaceable, and<note place="margin">Prov. 24. 21.</note> not conſult in matters of obedience with ſuch who refuſe to obey.</p>
                        <p n="7">7. In matters doubtful follow the ſafe Rule, hold that which is certain, leave that which is uncertain; leave rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, and obey the Magiſtrate that is certain. It is our duty.</p>
                        <p n="8">8. Hear reverend Dr. <hi>Sibs:</hi> who ſaith, The Laws under which we live are particular determinations of the Law of God, therefore ought to be a Rule unto us ſo far as they reach, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Sib's</hi> ſouls conflict, Edition firſt, fol. 364. pag. 2. I note the Edition becauſe later Editions have corrupted the Author; ſo that what he ſpeaks in general, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain to ſome things of the ſecond Table.</note> it be too narrow a Rule to be good, only ſo far as mans Law guides unto; yet love being the joynt reaſon and conſent of many men, for publique good hath an uſeful guidance of actions that fall under the ſame, where it<note place="margin">☞</note> daſheth not againſt God's Law; what is agreeable to Law, is agreeable to conſcience.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                           </label> If any of you ſay, as ſome do, Authority will not ſave ſouls.</head>
                        <p>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> Give me leave to tell them, That the Religious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Authority, ſuch as of <hi>David, Jehoſaphat, Joſiah, Hezekiah,</hi> for the keeping of the Paſſeover, and order in the ſervice of God; ſuch as of our Kings and Governours for the obſervation of the Lord's day, for the hearing and preaching of the Word, with other ſuch, did and doth ſave ſouls, and far more than your Meetings; yea, ſo much as a thing well and legally done, furthers it more than a thing done illegally and diſobediently. Beſides, if all which is taught in your private Meetings is good and warrantable, yet it is ſo far from converting, that it perverts many ſouls, cauſing them to judge amiſs of wholſom Laws and good Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, cauſing them to ſlight the Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, whom they are to hear and obey, making rents and diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Church, hardning Papiſts &amp; profane people in their unwarrantable ways, and making many well-minded people at a ſtand, not knowing what to do. And as it is certain that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41930:21"/> the commands of ſuch who are in Authority over us, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning matters of Religion, tend to the converſion and edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of men; ſo it is without all doubt, that diſobedience to their lawful commands, in lawful things, tends to the<note place="margin">Rom 13. 3.</note> damnation of ſouls.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                           </label> I will then ſubmit to the puniſhment inflicted according to Law.</head>
                        <p>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> But what if that is not ſufficient in point of conſcience? for Laws made of things juſt and profitable for humane ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, intend the ſubjects obedience in doing them, and are confirmed with a double bond; the wrath of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and conſcience towards God; by undergoing the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, the injury done to man is ſatisfied; but by reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Magiſtrate in intention, and breaking a profitable Law, a man remains under the pollution of ſin before God, from whom none can diſcharge.</p>
                        <p>The Law enjoyns publick Worſhip, and forbids ſuch pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Meetings; you neglect the publick Worſhip, and extol your private Meetings as the only way; you condemn the Law as unjuſt, and commend your ſo doing as good; whereas the Law tending to ſettle, preſerve and keep unity, peace, order and concord, muſt needs be good. And being ſo, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider whether ſuch Meetings can be ſo.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. Confronting and diſobeying lawful Authority.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Caſting dirt and diſgrace upon the face and form of Government, proclaiming it perſecuting and tyrannical, compelling ſuch good people as you would be accounted, to creep into Barns and Houſes, as if you wanted the truth publickly taught in our publick Meetings.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. Do you not in ſo doing, condemn our Church as falſe, if not Antichriſtian?</p>
                        <p n="4">4. Do you not condemn all the allowed Clergy, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable and naught?</p>
                        <p n="5">5. Do you not neglect and draw others to neglect the publick Ordinances of Chriſt?</p>
                        <p n="6">6. Do you not cauſe people to ſlight their Teachers, and to queſtion whether there be ſuch a thing as Religion, and ſo to turn Atheiſts?</p>
                        <p n="7">7. Do you not hereby cauſe people to think our Laws are
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41930:22"/> but ſcare-crows, and our Law-makers to be ſuch men who regard not what they do, ſo to undervalue the one and other?</p>
                        <p n="8">8. Do you not encourage your Teachers to do that they have no warrant to do from God or man? For what warrant have they to exerciſe the Miniſterial function, ſince the ſame Authority which enabled them to, diſinables them from preaching. It is the Law which inables us to, and allows us where, and when to preach; which Law hath power to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inable alſo. To this end ſee the judgment of the old Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts, in a Book put forth by Mr. <hi>William Rathband,</hi> in which they prove againſt Separatiſts, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is a true Church, and that ſeparation from it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful. Amongſt many other things they anſwer the Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſts objecting againſt them, their yielding to ſuſpenſions and deprivations, thus. That ſo long as the Biſhops ſuſpend and deprive, according to the Law of the Land, we account of the action herein, as of the act of the Church, which we may and ought to reverence and yield unto; if they do otherwiſe, we have liberty given us by the ſame Law to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal from them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                           </label> If it be ſaid that the Church is not to be obeyed when it ſuſpends and deprives us for ſuch cauſes, as we in our conſciences know to be inſufficient.</head>
                        <p>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> We anſwer (ſay they) That it lyeth in them to depoſe that may ordain, and they may ſhut that may open; and that as he may with a good conſcience execute a Miniſtry by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination and calling of the Church, who is privy to himſelf of ſome unfitneſs, if the Church will preſs him to it; ſo may he who is privy to himſelf of no fault that deſerveth deprivation, ceaſe from the execution of his Miniſtery, when he is preſſed thereunto by the Church. And if a guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs perſon put out of his charge by the Churches authority may yet continue in it, what proceeding can there be againſt guilty perſons, who in their own conceits are alwayes guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, or will at leaſt pretend ſo to be, ſeeing they alſo will be ready alwayes to object againſt the Churches judgment, that they are called of God, and may not therefore give
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41930:22"/> over the execution of their Miniſtry at the will of man.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                           </label> And to the ſpeech of the Apoſtles objected, <hi>Act. 4. 19, 20.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> They ſhew it is moſt unskilfully alledged, there being three differences between their caſe and the Apoſtles.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. They who inhibited the Apoſtles were known and profeſſed enemies to the Goſpel.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. The Apoſtles were charged not to teach in the name of Chriſt, nor to publiſh any part of the Doctrine of the Goſpel; which commandement might be more hardly yielded unto than this: Our Biſhops are not only content that the Goſpel ſhould be preached, but are alſo Preachers of it themſelves.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. The Apoſtles received not their calling and authority from men, nor by the hands of men, but immediately from God himſelf, and therefore alſo might not be reſtrained or depoſed by men—Whereas we, although we exerciſe a fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction whereof God is the Author, and we alſo called of God to it; yet are we called and ordained by the hands and Miniſtry of men, and may therefore by man be alſo depoſed and reſtrained from the exerciſe of our Miniſtry. Thus they. See alſo Mr. <hi>Bals</hi> tryal of the grounds of ſeparation, a ſolid work.</p>
                        <p n="9">9. Do not ſuch Meetings aſperſe all the penal Laws of the Land, and the judicial proceedings which have been ſince the Reformation, againſt Papiſts, Prieſts and Jeſuits, or any other juſtly ſuffering for their Religion as acts of higheſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice?</p>
                        <p n="10">10. Do they not endeavour the rending and crumbling our Church to nothing?</p>
                        <p n="11">11. Are they not a menas to fill the Kingdom full of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and tumults?</p>
                        <p n="12">12. Yea, and are they not againſt your ſo much cryed up Covenant, which was to bring the Church of God in the three Kingdoms to the neereſt uniformity in Religion; whereas you by thus doing, go about to divide and ſubdivide, not being ignorant what fruits our Saviour ſhews to come<note place="margin">Mat. 12. 25.</note> from diviſion; ſaying, <hi>A Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf</hi> (po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical, good Laws and conſtitutions, Eccleſiaſtical, as do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41930:23"/> and diſcipline) brings deſolation, probably, and very often. Look but to the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> what deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons! Their preaching an empty thing, when one for this, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 12. 1. Cor. 11. 20.</note> for that. Their Communions became deſolate, and by ſuch means and doings St. <hi>Paul</hi> became their enemy, who gave them their very being in faith, and was their ſpiritual father. And what deſolation ſuch diviſions bring with us, is evident; what caſting off your Preachers, their old pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, and your old practiſes, until at length ſome grow from ſomething to nothing. Is it not ſo when ſome noted for parts and piety long ſince, a long time talk ſo Atheiſtically as to profeſs a readineſs to hear the one and the other, with a reſolution to believe neither, the one preaching againſt the other; and that there was never any ſound preaching ſince Chriſt's time. Are theſe good fruits? and would not ſuch have objected the ſame againſt the Prophets, Apoſtles, and Chriſt himſelf? falſe Prophets and Apoſtles preaching a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the true. Chriſt preaching againſt the Scribes and Phariſees, and they affirming him to be a deceiver? And I dare maintain that what they preach contrary to what we preach in publick (if they do) to be contrary to ſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                           </label> You ſay you do nothing but what is good, you ſet open the great doors, and little doors, not caring who ſees, who heareth you.</head>
                        <p n="1">
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> 1. Admit that what is preached is good, yet it is not well done; good things ſhould be well done, according to rule and order.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. The Tree is known by the fruits, and by your ſuch Meetings, we ſee the publick Ordinances ſlighted, neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, contemned.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. I cannot accuſe what is delivered in your Meetings; but if it is contrary to what we preach in publick, it is not good doctrine. And let me tell you, that <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed his dangerous opinions in private Meetings; and how our Mr. <hi>Thrask</hi> in publick preached ſound truths, but in his private Meetings, he did indoctrinate his followers with his pernicious principles.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                           </label> They who preach to us in private Meetings, are pious men, the other are profane, vicious, ſcandalous.</head>
                        <p n="1">
                           <pb n="39" facs="tcp:41930:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> 1. If this be true that ſome of us are ſuch, we are ſorry for it; yea, ſuch we will not juſtifie (and when was it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe?) nor is all done by the other juſtifiable.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. There are more ſins than ſwearing and drunkenneſs; who can forget the ſwarms of ſins in our late Tragedies? and who were actors of many of them in it?</p>
                        <p n="3">3. For the preſent. Are not deſpiſing of Authority, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience<note place="margin">Cobler of <hi>Gloc.</hi>
                           </note> to wholſom Laws, ſins? from which are theſe men free?</p>
                        <p n="4">4. Bleſſed be God, although we all are proclaimed to be profane and naught; yet there are very many as free from idleneſs, drunkenneſs, ſwearing, and ſuch like vices, and as painful, pious, charitable, and inoffenſive as the ſtricteſt in your commanded company.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. But to be plain with you; All profeſſions whilſt kept under, it is their intereſt to be orderly; but when theſe men of late had their liberty, we are able to prove the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane exceſſes of ſome of them, even to publick ſcandal, by Epicuriſm, intemperance and uncleanneſs; to ſay no more.</p>
                        <p>For my part I cannot think, but that the reſpect ſuch who are in Authority bear to themſelves; their care to have their Laws and Religion upholden, their obedient Clergy not vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, and people kept from Atheiſm and rebellion, will awaken them in time, ſtrictly and by ſeverity, to do that which their clemency will not do. You cry out much againſt Popery, yet your doings endeavour to bring it in, and ſet it up; it is a Jeſuitical plot to ſow diviſion amongſt us, to make our Religion odious, and that they may fiſh in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled waters. From a good Author I will tell you a ſtory, which is this. Before our troubles, one <hi>Meridith,</hi> an ancient<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Nicolſ.</hi>
                           </note> and learned Jeſuit, told one reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that in <hi>England</hi> they had been long and induſtrious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the work of converſion, but it went on ſlowly, and ſo would do, until they took a wiſer courſe. Two things there were that muſt be done, before they ſhould bring their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs to a full effect; they muſt firſt find a way to remove the Biſhops and Miniſters, in whoſe rooms they muſt bring
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41930:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> it ſo about, that all ſhould have liberty to preach. Then ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, they muſt get down the Common-prayer-Book, and ſuffer every man to uſe what prayer he liſt. And we cannot but remember how far they effected this in our ſad troubles. Beſides, if you expect ſuch priviledge, why may not they expect the ſame? They being Chriſtians, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubjects, they and ſome of you being Recuſants; why not they their Maſs, as well as you your Meetings?</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                           </label> Why? Thoſe you hear in your Meetings have rare gifts, they are pious and precious men.</head>
                        <p>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> I envy no mans gifts, but bleſs God for other mens parts and piety.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Compariſons are odious, otherwiſe we could ſay as St. <hi>Paul</hi> of the falſe Apoſtles in his time; Are they thus, and ſo? ſo are we.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. The forbidden fruit without doubt was excellent, yet it had been good for our firſt Parents to have contented themſelves with their allowed Trees and fruits. Many mens Wives and Diet come ſhort of other mens, yet it is fit their own ſhould content them.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. Bleſſed be God your allowance is large, you may hear every week three Sermons in an approved way, and none of them to be contemned.</p>
                        <p>And as for Popiſh Prieſts, do you not think the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> will ſay for their Prieſts and Jeſuits, the ſame that you do for your Preachers; you ſay yours are rarely gifted men, great Scholars, pious, painful, and what you will more. They will not conform to the Book of Common-prayer, nor obſerve the Orders appointed by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they will not aſſent and conſent. They can and will ſay the ſame of theirs. If you ſay yours will take no Livings, they can ſay the ſame, and add; not Wives neither. If you ſay that yours live by providence, going about to do good, they can ſay theirs have no ſetled abiding but are ſometimes here and there to promote and ſpread the Catholick cauſe, and are maintained by the peoples bounty.</p>
                        <p>We acknowledge that we and Papiſts are Chriſtians, agreeing in many things; for we and they acknowledge
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41930:24"/> unity in Trinity; but we with them acknowledge no Queen of heaven to pray unto. We and they acknowledge the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be the Word of God; but we with them make not the Apocrypha Canonical. We with them make the Word of God the ground of faith; but we with them make not unwritten traditions of equal authority. We and they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in admitting doctrinal traditions agreeing with Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or thence deduced; yea, ritual for order and decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy left to the diſpoſition of the Church, although but of poſitive and humane right, they not being childiſh, nor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted parts of God's Worſhip; nor with opinion of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, nor burdenſom for multitude: But we with them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not traditions obtruded as Articles of Religion, grounds of faith, and parts of God's Worſhip, they not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deduced from Scripture by inference, nor expreſly commanded, ſuch we reject. We and they receive and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the three Creeds; but we with them receive not the Creed of <hi>Trent.</hi> We and they believe the true God is to be worſhipped in Spirit and truth; we with them believe not that he is to be worſhipped by Images. We and they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that we are to pray with fervency and ſincerity; but we with them pray not in an unknown tongue. We and they pray to God; but we with them do not pray to Saints and Angels. We and they acknowledge Chriſt to be our Mediator of redemption and interceſſion; but we with them do not at all rely upon the interceſſion and merits of Saints and Angels. We and they do honour Saints depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but we with them do not worſhip them. We and they do urge to good works; we as neceſſary effects of juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grace, they as cauſes; we as the way wherein we muſt walk unto, they as the meritorious cauſe of eternal felicity. We with them believe two Sacraments; but we with them believe not ſeven. We and they believe a real preſence, ſo in the Sacrament, that the worthy Communicant really partakes of Chriſt's body and blood ſpiritually; but we with them do not believe that the bread is tranſubſtantiated into the body and blood of Chriſt; ſo that dogs and mice may eat it. We and they believe there is an heaven and hell;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41930:25"/> but we with them believe not Purgatory. Chriſtians there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                           </label> But they are Idolaters.</head>
                        <p n="1">
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> 1. And they ſay we are Hereticks and Schiſmaticks. Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only proves nothing.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Call them Idolaters (I think they are ſo) and what you pleaſe; yet I am ſure as in many things you differ from them: for whereas they make ſeven Sacraments, ſome of you will not make uſe of two. They aſcribe too much to Sacraments, you too little. They keep too many holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, ſome of you keep none. They are blamed for ſaying the Lords prayer too often, ſome of you for not at all. So, in ſome things you agree, namely, in Separation and Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſancy. They forſake our Church as Heretical, ſome of you as Antichriſtian, I fear, ſince you are come to ſay our Church and yours.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                           </label> Say we not right, that your Church is Antichriſtian, ſince your Common-prayer-Book is Popery? taken out of the Maſs-Book? how can we then abide it? may we not juſtly leave it, and for it your Aſſemblies?</head>
                        <p n="1">
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> 1. Take heed what you ſay, the firſt offence is an hundred marks; the ſecond four hundred marks, and impriſonment; the third is loſs of all a mans goods, and impriſonment du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life. Laws which ſleep a while may be awakened.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. But what one word or ſyllable is in it ſavouring of Popery? Is there any praying to Saints? for the dead? Is there any allowance of merits? of Purgatory? name any one point of Popery if you can.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. Whereas you ſay it was taken out of the Maſs-Book; who told you ſo? did you or they ever ſee the Maſs-Book? do you or they know what it is? But admit it is taken out of it, and that the Maſs-Book is bad, as it is; Is it the worſe? Is gold refined from droſs, wheat cleanſed from chaff, at all the worſe for the droſs and chaff? As for the Maſs, I abhor it, as injurious to the Prieſthood of Chriſt, to the ſacrifice or death of Chriſt, as an hindrance to an holy life, and contrary to Gods will, and therefore I am far from defending it. The word <hi>Miſſa</hi> or Maſs, by ſome is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41930:25"/> of <hi>Miſſoth,</hi> or <hi>Mincha,</hi> an Oblation; by ſome from the Latins, who uſed theſe words, <hi>Miſſus, Miſſa,</hi> &amp;c. The ancient <hi>Roman</hi> Idolaters diſmiſſed the people from their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>fices with theſe words; I, <hi>licet, Miſſa eſt;</hi> Depart, it is permitted, and ſo the Aſſembly was diſmiſſed. And theſe words are now pronounced, <hi>Ite, Miſſa eſt (ſcilicet concio ſive Eccleſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>)</hi> ſignifying a leave given to the company to depart. Let it be what it will, or come from this or that, we have it not, neither name, nor thing. Demand of them I deſire you, who inform you that our Common-prayer-Book is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the Maſs-Book, ſo Popery; If ever they ſaw and read the Maſs-Book? And if they have ſeen and read it, demand of them then, 1. Whether all the Maſs-Book is in our Common-prayer-Book? They muſt ſay no. 2. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all our Common-prayer-Book is in the Maſs-Book? They muſt ſay no. 3. Whether that which is in our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer, and in the Maſs-Book, is good or bad? They cannot but ſay it is all good. I am perſwaded they can prove none of it to be bad. 4. Whether it being good, the being of it in the Maſs-Book, can make it bad? or whether we are to reject all the good in Popery, as the name of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, with much more?</p>
                        <p>Mr. <hi>William Rathband</hi> (who put forth a modeſt confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Separatiſts agreed upon long before, as he ſaith, by the joint conſent of the godly and learned Miniſters of this Kingdom, who ſtood out and ſuffered in the caſe of Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. They in it ſhewing the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be a true Church of Chriſt, and therefore ſeparation from it to be unlawful.) He with Mr. <hi>Thomas Langley,</hi> Mr. <hi>Simeon Aſh,</hi> Mr. <hi>Francis Woodcock,</hi> and Mr. <hi>George Croſſe,</hi> all ſo far as I can conjecture, Non-conformiſts, put forth a Book of Mr. <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>n Ball,</hi> a Non-conformiſt; wherein he writes learnedly and<note place="margin">The tryal of the grounds of ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he put forth himſelf.</note> piouſly againſt Separation; he writes in defence of ſett forms of prayer, and that men are not to ſeparate from the Church becauſe of ours. He ſaith, many are the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are made againſt ſett forms of prayers, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41930:26"/> particularly againſt our Book of Common-prayer; all which I have endeavoured (ſaith he) to anſwer ſeverally; not becauſe they are of ſo great weight, but becauſe I deſired to ſatisfie fully every doubt. And whereas it was objected, The Common-prayer-Book was taken out of the Maſs-Book. He ſaith, It followeth not that therefore it is a<note place="margin">Pag. 8.</note> falſe worſhip; for many things in the Maſs-Book are good, a pearl may be found upon a dunghil. 2. If out of the Maſs-Book, How cometh it to paſs then, ſaith he, that it hath thoſe things directly contrary to the Maſs-Book? He inſtanceth in many. Further, he ſaith, It is more proper to ſay the Maſs was taken out of our Common-prayer; for<note place="margin">Pag. 10.</note> moſt things in our Common-prayer were to be found in Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies long before the Maſs. The prayers and truths of God taught in that Book, pertain to the Church as her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative;<note place="margin">Pag. 11.</note> the Church of God may lawfully make claim to thoſe holy things, which Antichriſt hath unjuſtly uſurped. Now ſince I find that erroneous opinions once entertained are not eaſily gotten out of the heads and hearts of men, for they quickly root deep; take ſtrong hold, and cannot eaſily be pull'd up, as we ſee in Chriſt's time. The Phariſees held corrupt opinions about<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 15. 2.</note> working,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 7. 11.</note> diſpencing with childrens obedience, about<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 23. 32, 33.</note> ſwearing,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Luk. 15. 12.</note> faſting, and many errors about the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> Law. Did Chriſt get theſe errors out of them? He brought the cleereſt light that ever any did; they for all that lived in darkneſs. The Sadduces de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the<note n="(f)" place="margin">Mat. 22. 23.</note> reſurrection. Chriſt laboured to convince them, they held their errors in St. <hi>Pauls</hi>
                           <note n="(g)" place="margin">Act. 23. 8.</note> time.<note n="(h)" place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 20. 2 Tim. 2. 18.</note> 
                           <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineus,</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> had rather be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to Satan, than to deliver up their corrupt and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble opinions, Therefore as all of us ſhould be careful to take heed what opinions we receive, to this end to try the ſpirits, &amp; not take things on truſt for the learning, ſeeming holineſs and worth, or reſpect we have to any man; but to ſearch and ſee that they have a ſound bottoming from the Word: So we are not to wonder why the beſt of God's meſſengers can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take men off from their unwarranted opinions. The Jews retain their opinion, that neither <hi>Elijah</hi> nor Chriſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41930:26"/> are come. The Papiſts retain their opinions, and will die in their errors rather than embrace the truth. It will be no ſtrange thing then, if I endeavouring to, I neither do nor can remove you from your erroneous practiſes.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. In vilifying, not coming to, but abſenting your ſelves from the publick prayers of the Church, no not by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the teſtimony of holy Martyrs, the hatred Papiſts bear to it, the ſtrictneſs of the Law under which we live, the excellency and uſefulneſs of it, nor by the approbation the Reformed Churches give of it; of all which I have made uſe but in vain.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. In not baptizing your children, or baptizing them in an illegal and irregular way, although I think I have ſhewed ſufficient grounds and authorities, and Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> opinion, which is, That they who deny baptiſm to their children play the devils part, yea, do herein heinouſly exceed the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. Some who admire the man, will be his Interpreter, ſaying, his meaning is, If they may have them baptized in his way, and then will not, but refuſe. Read his Book of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Church-memberſhip through and through, and you ſhall find no ſuch limitting to this way or that; he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth ours to be true baptiſm, valid, and not to be reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated. And whereas ſome who think they know more than they do, ſay, It is the duty of parents to have their children baptized, although it doth children no good; ſuch ſenſleſs ſilly ſpeeches ſhew that ſome folks bolts are ſoon ſhot. It is a duty, and yet doth it no good? Do Scriptures ſo highly<note place="margin">Act. 23. 8. Rom. 6. 4. Tit. 3. 4.</note> commend Baptiſm as we read, and doth it no good? Is it no good to be a member of Chriſt's Church, but to be in the ſame condition with Turks and Pagans?</p>
                        <p n="3">3. In not coming to the Communion, of which I have ſpoken often, and at large; but I ſee you are reſolved not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding. I will intreat you to take notice, that if your practiſes are erroneous, as they are, 1. That to be obſtinate in an error is dangerous for mans ſalvation. The uglineſs of obſtinacy in error doth appear from the Author of it, who<note place="margin">Mat. 5. 19. Mat. 13. 25.</note> is not God, but the Devil; ſo obſtinate errors, diabolical; and naturally it produceth Hereſie or Schiſm, and is ſuch
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41930:27"/> that St. <hi>Paul</hi> wiſhed to be cut of. A mutinous Soldier is<note place="margin">Gal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5. 12.</note> hanged, when an open enemy hath fair quarter. Conſider alſo that errors in the end bring terrors, ſuch making men like children, hulk on the Sea without rudder; for in ſuch a condition are ſuch who flote on groundleſs errors; yea, errors<note place="margin">Eph. 4. 14.</note> make men as bones out of joint, which coſt groans to bring them in place again. Alas! what is a traveller in the night out of the way? how is he troubled? A Rebel out of the Kings favour, how is he perplexed? erroneous perſons are Travellers out of the way, and as Rebels out of favour.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                           </label> You are deceived, Papiſts, Anabaptiſts, Quakers, we and other more, you think do err, are not troubled; we fear not, we ſuffer for our conſciences.</head>
                        <p>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> Admit ſome live and die confident in groſs errors, never fearing harms to follow: So ſome run into the fire fearleſly, and ruſh upon dangers deſperately, but they are frantick or fooliſh, not wiſe and well-guided perſons.</p>
                        <p>And that we may not err, take heed of pride which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokes men to errors and factions. Take heed of prejudice againſt any thing cauſeleſly. Take heed of covetouſneſs,<note place="margin">Act. 8. 9. Act. 19. 32 Tit. 1. 11.</note> truths adverſary; for ſome ſubvert houſes for lucre ſake; gain perſwades many to maintain errors, that errors may maintain them. And be we careful to this end conſtantly to believe what is taught you by the Scripture, and conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to obey what is commanded you by the Church; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ded it be not contrary to Scripture. Be careful to faſten our faith upon Scripture. If Scripture ſaith it, I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve<note place="margin">Gal. 1. 8.</note> it. To faſten our charity upon our Mother the Church, and her directions, and ſee that we our ſelves be humble; for whereas many object, all alledge Scripture, we confeſs it to<note place="margin">Mat. 4.</note> be ſo: The Devil himſelf did ſo; yet it is certain, if we will read the Scriptures carefully and faithfully, hear the Church charitably, and eſteem of our ſelves modeſtly, we ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand Scriptures ſufficiently to keep us from error.</p>
                        <p>Once again let me intreat you brethren, not to err with any Maſter. Some think they may ſafely do this or that becauſe of ſuch whom they follow: To them I ſay as St. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>guſtine</hi> of <hi>Cyprian;</hi> Although there are many things that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41930:27"/> 
                           <hi>Cyprian</hi> did excellently teach, yet there are ſome things wherein <hi>Cyprian</hi> might have learned more than he knew: So ſay I of ſome men, ſuch ſhall be my friends, I love them well for the good ſervice they may do, but I muſt, and do love the truth better, ſince a wiſe man will not alter an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient truth for the love he bears to the Author of any novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,<note place="margin">Gal. 1. 8.</note> and a good man dare not. For although men are won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully pleaſed with their own conceits, and their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt be the great Monarch, to rule even the Monarchs of the world, although they ſuppreſs truth, to advance falſhoods; yet they are but like a cumberſom heap of ſands; a congeſted heap of groundleſs opinions good for nothing, not worth any thing, only fit to deceive here, and to deſtroy hereafter; a fruitleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> heap bearing no other fruit than to abuſe our neighbour, diſhonour God, and betray mens ſouls to Satan; a diſagreeing heap not faſt joyned together. Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and falſhoods may for a time be patch'd together, like a beggars cloak; but they continue not long united, and an inconſiſtent heap; for they who embrace errors, are not long conſtant, but run from one abſurdity to another: Let me therefore acquaint you how ſome have drawn, and do draw well-meaning people into error, being ſtirred there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. Sometimes by covetouſneſs. <hi>Paulus Samoſetanus</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting preferment from the Queen of <hi>Arabia,</hi> fell into ſuch Schiſms, which in the end wrought his own overthrow. Some men finding it an eaſie thing to live at another mans Table (although ſo doing is baſe to a generous mind) ſpeak often, things to maintain and pleaſe a faction, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 11.</p>
                        <p>Sometimes by ambition which hath often cauſed conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſeparation, becauſe <hi>Arrius</hi> could not get the Biſhopwrick of <hi>Alexand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ia; Donatus</hi> of <hi>Carthage; Aerius</hi> of <hi>Ponts,</hi> they became enemies to the Church.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. Sometimes by intollerable pride working contempt of Authority, the contempt of which cauſeth ſeparation; and mens ſelf-love is the cauſe of this contempt. Self-love as<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Lib.</hi> 14. cap. 18. <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>civitat. Dei.</hi>
                           </note> St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, Is the maſter builder which buildeth the City of the Devil; for when men are ſo beſotted with opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41930:28"/> of themſelves, that they think their own writings to be Goſpel, and Pigmaleon-like, fall in love with images of their own making; they will ſooner hazard their lives, than by revoking their errors impair their reputation. Tell them of general Councels, of many learned men, they think they all might err ſooner than themſelves. If you alledge to them the judgment of the ancient Fathers, they are ready to ſay with <hi>Abailardus,</hi> Although all the Fathers thought ſo, yet I do not think ſo; Fathers are but children, Schoolmen<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Bois.</hi>
                           </note> (as one ſaith) are but Foolmen in reſpect of themſelves, who can ſooner eſpy moats in the Fathers eyes, than beams of folly and ignorance in their own eyes. Tell them of Mr. <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>d,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bolton,</hi> Dr. <hi>Tayler,</hi> and ſuch other (who liv'd not long ſince in our own times) what they taught, how they liv'd, they can preſently ſay; ſuch were good men in their times, but now we have new lights, and are better gifted.</p>
                        <p>Let me alſo intreat you to conſider what hurt you do, what ſad inconveniences your ſeparations and diviſions do bring, how they diſtract people, ſo that they know not what to do. <hi>Bartholomew Caſanus</hi> a <hi>Sap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>niſh</hi> Biſhop, tells us a ſtory of a <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Prieſt, deſirous to baptize an <hi>Indian</hi> Noble man; the <hi>Indian</hi> asked the Prieſt, whither the <hi>Spaniards</hi> dying went? The Prieſt ſaid, to heaven: The <hi>Indian</hi> replyed, he would not go whither ſuch cruel people went. There is alſo a ſtory of <hi>Bernardine Ochin,</hi> a man of great learning, who diſliking the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> fled to <hi>Geneva</hi> firſt, from thence to <hi>England,</hi> where ſeeing ſo many Sects, all challenging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be true, and each condemning the other, he turned back to <hi>Rome,</hi> ſaying, It was impoſſible, that they who were ſo ſimple, ſo way-ward, ſo obſtinate, ſo full of Sects and diſſentions, could be of the true faith of Chriſt. Suppoſe a Pagan ſhould come and ſay, I would willingly be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and ſeeing ſuch ſtrife and diſſentions amongſt us; one man ſaying he holds the truth; Another ſaith no, but he is in the right, what ſhall this poor Pagan do?</p>
                        <p>And let me deſire to know what will pleaſe and content you; you extol Mr. <hi>Bolton,</hi> he deſerved the ſame (but take
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41930:28"/> heed it be not like the Phariſees commending the old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,<note place="margin">Mat. 23. 29.</note> your doings being contrary to his preaching and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe) do you follow his doctrine and example, then we are all agreed, we ſhall have no ſuch dividings; you gathered hands againſt me to caſt me out, and to bring in Mr. <hi>Baſely,</hi> you had your deſire (for then you might do what you liſt) you thought your ſelves happy in your change; How long did he pleaſe you? were you not then gadders this way, and that way, to this man, and that man, eſpecially to one whom after you abhorr'd, for doing but his duty? were you not then condemned for your giddy waywardneſs? For my carriage amongſt you, I ſhame not to own it, and I challenge envy it ſelf to ſay the worſt it can, when and where I may anſwer for my life and doctrine. I am not like to be a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to you long as a man, muchleſs as a Preacher, being ſo far ſtricken in age; I having therefore often uſed argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and reaſons to diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>vade you from divers erroneous practiſes, and thus far now diſcharged my duty in ſhewing the danger of error, and wherein you groſly err, if I err not, (as I am perſwaded I do not) and ſince all ſuch perſwaſions are in vain, and prevail not; it being no little grief to me to ſee (as ſome other) ſo your neglect (to ſay no worſe) of Catechiſing and Communions, for the remedying of which I did formerly complain of one (without any ill will to the party) hoping that it might do good to him and others; but only complaining and no more, and keeping off the ſentence intended, no good was thereby done. Now again, out of the love I bear to you, not bearing malice to the party, or any mans perſon; nor by reſpect to my ſelf (ſince the ſmaller the Communions are, and no Catechiſing, I have the more eaſe and leſs labour.) And out of the regard I bear to mine own ſoul, in omitting no lawful means unattempted to do you good, I am conſidering whether it will not be my duty, out of the many refuſers of Communions and Catechiſing, to ſingle out one who may be ſuppoſed in every reſpect beſt able to manage and defend ſuch unwonted irregularities, that ſo it may appear whether you have any grounds for ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warranted courſes; and whether thoſe in authority have
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41930:29"/> power to keep us in order, and to ſuch neceſſary duties, ſince by Sects and Schiſms, Sectaries and Separatiſts, their ignorance and ſimplicity, their diviſions and obſtinacy, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in our unhappy <hi>England</hi> are caſt down, who were deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to ſtand in the truth of God; many are hindred from being Proteſtants, and more turned Recuſants; many their hearts ſo ſhaken, that Camelion-like, they are capable of any ſave the right faith. It being the property of Hereticks, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, to weary the ſtrong, to catch the weak in a ſnare, and to leave the middle ſort ſcrupulous. I therefore now reſolve no longer by ſilence and fitting ſtill, to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſo much hurt; and for this end to make trial ſo far forth as I have ſaid, what good I can that way do, ſome men being forced with rigour, who will not be refelled with reaſons, from their erroneous wayes. As in the Ark there was bread (Manna) for refection, alſo a rod for correction: So in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Church of Chriſt, there is a voice of conſolation to defend the good as with a ſhield, and a voice of correction to order the ſtubborn and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient. The Church of Chriſt therefore according to St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> is called the handmaid of the Lord; ſo the Miſtris of her people to guide and rule her folk, yea and to correct<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Aguſt. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi> 50. <hi>ad Bonif. de corig. he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. epiſt.</hi> 48.</note> them to, when they offend as <hi>Sarah</hi> did <hi>Hagar</hi> when ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned her Miſtris. I believe <hi>Hagar</hi> thought <hi>Sarah</hi> dealt hardly with her, whereas ſhe did more perſecute <hi>Sarah</hi> by her contempt and wicked pride, than <hi>Sarah</hi> did her by ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her out of doors. There being alſo little hopes of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heard or regarded amongſt deaf and ſelf-conceited men, who regard the cenſures of the Church no more than a bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let of cork; it is good to try, and ſee whether they have a rod (power) and can uſe it; for every one is not a friend who ſpareth, nor every one a foe who ſmiteth; yea, it is a mercy ſometimes to puniſh, and oftentimes it is cruelty to ſpare. Such a Father who ſpareth his ſervant, killing his ſon, will be thought unjuſt, not merciful; and what can we think of them who ſpare thoſe who rend and tear the Church our Mother? Bad men through malice do unjuſtly hurt and vex the godly without cauſe; and good men through love by
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41930:29"/> diſcipline do juſtly correct others for their miſcarriages. The diſcipline of the Church being as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, the preſerver of hope, the guide to ſalvation, the retainer of faith, and cheriſher of godlineſs. The correcting voice of diſcipline oft doth and may do good to ſuch who will not be moved with the ſweet voice of intreating. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, He who binds a frantick man, and awakes him who is in a Lethargy, is troubleſom to both; yet he loveth and helpeth both: So to bind men with the cords of juſtice, that they may not wrong themſelves and others, is a great good; it being alſo far better to weaken ſome by juſtice, than ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to go on to weaken others by faction.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="objection">
                        <head>
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                           </label> But if I will complain for neglecting Communions and Chate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing, why not of ſwearers and drunkards?</head>
                        <p n="1">
                           <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                           </label> 1. I hear no oaths, I ſee no drunkards; I ſee abſenters from God's Ordinances, and I preach againſt the one and the other.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Moſt ſpeak againſt ſwearing and drunkenneſs as groſs ſins; the other go under the notion of goodneſs.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. Swearers and drunkards deny not our Church to be a true Church, they deny not the Ordinances; and they might be better wrought upon and reformed, was it not for our diviſions. The other do little leſs than ſeek the overthrow of the Church.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. I hope I am a friend to no vice, and ſuch an enemy to all, that if any will bring me as good evidence, and will ſtand to it, that ſuch and ſuch are incorrigible ſwearers and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, as I have that ſuch and ſuch come not to Communions; if I then endeavour not their amendment by Church-cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures (if I cannot by perſwaſions) let me be blamed. I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not to create any juſt offence, or real hurt to any mans perſon; for truly I know not the man living, or creature breathing to whom I do not heartily wiſh, grace, mercy and peace. My deſire is to endeavour in this place, to ſtop the current of opinioniſts blown by the ſpirit of error o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver many parts of this Land, to the diſhonour of God, and endangering of many a mans ſalvation, and ſtaggering well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaning people, and drawing them to diſobedience, Schiſm,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41930:30"/> and Faction. And whilſt I am ſo doing, &amp; when I have done, I hope to make it appear, that as I never yet did ſhew the leaſt malice nor diſcontent to them who formerly ſought to ruine me and mine; ſo that now I bear not any ill will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the party, or any other, but that I do what I do in love; and that if they make tryal, they may truly ſay of me, as it became a Proverb concerning Arch-biſhop <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; Do my Lord of</hi> Canterbury <hi>a ſhrewd turn, and then you may be ſure to have him your friend for your labour whilſt you live.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Thus you and I being men are ſubject to err, and it being dangerous to live in error, according to my Office and duty I have declared wherein you err, that I may not be guilty of the ſame by my ſilence. If you can bring me convincing grounds that I thus differing from you in judgment, and in thus diſcharging my duty do err, you ſhall ſoon perceive and ſee that I will not be obſtinate in error. And if what I have ſaid contain convincing arguments to make it clear that you do err, then I deſire the ſame of you, that you may not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately perſiſt in error; that ſo both I and you may follow this bleſſed counſel of the holy Ghoſt, by the Apoſtle Saint <hi>James</hi> ſpeaking to you and me in theſe words, <hi>Do not err my beloved brethren.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Preached <date>
                           <hi>October</hi> 6, 13, 20.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="collection_of_sayings">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:41930:30"/>
                  <head>Certain ſayings of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his Infant-Church-memberſhip.</head>
                  <p>THe main ſcope of their endeavours in publick and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate is to propagate their opinions, and if they preach any wholſom doctrine, it is uſually ſubſervient to their great deſign, that the truth may be as ſuger to ſweeten their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,<note place="margin">Pag. 144.</note> that they may be eaſier ſwallowed. They perſwade the people that Miniſters are ſeducers, lyars, &amp;c. judge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note place="margin">16.</note> what good may people expect from Miniſters. How hath it grieved my ſpirit to ſee and hear men profeſſing to be more godly than others, to make it the buſineſs of their lives to diſgrace the Miniſters of the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>When poor people hear thoſe deſpiſe the Miniſtry, that<note place="margin">16.</note> once were conſtant hearers—Sure theſe men having tryed, ſee ſome evil in that way, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>O how it ſtumbleth and drives off the poor ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple<note place="margin">145.</note> from Religion, when they ſee thoſe that have ſeemed Religious prove ſuch? And when they ſee us at ſuch diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence one with another; and when they ſee ſo many Sects and Parties, that they know not which to turn to; They think that all ſtrictneſs doth tend to this, and ſo that the godly are but a company of giddy, proud, unſettled, ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons, that know not where to ſtep, till they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides themſelves. O! how are the Papiſts hardened by this? I have ſpoken with ſome of them that once began to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate—who now upon the obſervation of theſe Sects—are generally confirmed in their way, and ſay, Now you may ſee what it is to depart from the boſom of the Church—to make the Scriptures common, &amp;c. The Epiſcopal Party are more confirmed in their way by it, and ſay, You have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the matter well, &amp;c. yea, thoſe who were offended at the Prelates cruelty—do now think they did well, and that which was needful for the quenching of this fire, whilſt it<note place="margin">When? to whom?</note> was a ſpark. And many who began to ſtagger at the Kings late Wars, are now many thouſands of them perſwaded of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41930:31"/> the lawfulneſs of it, from the miſcarriages of theſe men. And if report (too probable) do not lye, thouſands and<note place="margin">And other grounds.</note> millions of Papiſts in all Countreys of <hi>Europe</hi> where they dwell, are confirmed and hardened in their Religion, by the odious reports that go of the miſcarriages of theſe men in <hi>England.</hi> Theſe ſay they, are your Reformers. And this is your Reformation. How many thouſand Profeſſors of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion are quite ruined in their ſouls, and turned into Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters rather than Saints? How many ſad, diſtracted, divided Congregations? What dividing and ſubdividing, and ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding<note place="margin">149.</note> again, and running from Church to Church, and from opinion to opinion, till ſome are at ſuch a loſs, that they affirm Chriſt hath no Church, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>How many diſtracted Families in <hi>England</hi> that were wont to worſhip God in unity and joyfulneſs? One will pray, and the other will not pray with him, becauſe he is unbaptized;<note place="margin">16.</note> and a third ſaith Family-duties are not commanded in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. One will ſing praiſe to God, another ſcorneth it, as if it were ſinging of a Jig; and a third will ſing Pſalms from the dictate of the Spirit only—One will be of one Church, and another of another: Envying and ſtrife hath taken place, while unity and love are laid aſide, becauſe that truth is joſled out by error.</p>
                  <p>What a multitude do I know, that are moſt notorious for<note place="margin">150.</note> pride, thinking themſelves wiſer than the ableſt Teachers, when they have need to be chatechiſed? Some of them run up into the Pulpit to preach, ſome will not come in publick, are conſtant Teachers in private, where they vilifie the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, and make poor ſouls believe, that the Miniſters are ignorant of the truth of God in compariſon of them.</p>
                  <p>I have wondred formerly why St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt<note place="margin">151.</note> Hereſies and Schiſms, and what made even all the primitive Fathers ſpend moſt of their zeal &amp; painful writings againſt Hereſies and Errors? as doth <hi>Ignatius:</hi> and almoſt all, when we in theſe dayes were ready to think theſe to be ſcarce ſins? But now we begin to know their meaning; and I can ſay as good <hi>Dadianus,</hi> I never knew what Hereſie or Schiſm was till now.</p>
                  <p>Thus he and abundance more.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:41930:31"/>
                  <p> A DISSWASIVE FROM ERROR A PERSWASIVE TO ORDER</p>
                  <p>By a Lover of, and Labourer for Truth, Peace, Unanimity, Uniformity and Order, <hi>Joſeph Bentham.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>JUDE 3.</bibl>
                     <p>Earneſtly contend for the faith which was once delivered to the Saints.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. R.</hi> MDCLXIX.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:41930:32"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:41930:32"/>
                  <head>A Viſitation-Sermon PREACHED At <hi>Kettering,</hi> Octob. 6, 15. 1666.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>1 COR. 14. 40.</bibl>
                        <p>Let all things be done decently and in order.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ANY enormities and diſorders were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> inceſt unpuniſhed bolſtered, not lamented; Law-ſuits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Pagans, to the ſcandal of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; men covered, women uncovered in Divine Service; negligent and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy coming to the Lord's Table; abuſing of gifts to vain glory, denying the reſurrection, &amp;c. The Apoſtle having handled ſome things concerning mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of decency, as womens praying covered in token of ſubjection, and mens praying or prophecying (namely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent at praying and prophecying) uncovered in ſign of their ſuperiority. Having alſo ſpoken of ſome things more properly pertaining to edification, by ſilencing ſuch who uſed tongues without interpretation, and of ſome things
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41930:33"/> peculiar to order, as to ſpeak by two or three; in the cloſe he ſets down a rule or Canon, by which all muſt be ſquared; a touchſtone to try, and a ballance to weigh Church-orders, whether they be right; which they are. In regard of the end, <hi>v.</hi> 26. when they tend to edification; and in regard of the manner, when they are done decently and in order; ſince all things ſhould be done without confuſion of perſons, and proceedings in juſt and due order; therefore what is in the Church, as it is to be decent, ſo it ought to be in order.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>Order in the Church of God, is a good and an excellent thing.</hi> And it is ſo,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In regard of God, who is a God of order, <hi>v.</hi> 33. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der proceeds from him, and from his throne, who alſo is a lover of it, delighting in it; all loving their own works, and what conforms to them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In regard of the Church, which in Scripture is called<note n="(a)" place="margin">Cant. 4. 12.</note> a garden encloſed, therefore to kept in order; an<note n="(b)" place="margin">Cant. 6. 4.</note> army with banners, therefore to march, and to be Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalled in order. And<note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 15.</note> Gods houſe, therefore to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned and kept in order.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In regard of good men who ſo prized order, That the<note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Chr. 5. 55.</note> Prieſts are commended for keeping order. They are<note n="(e)" place="margin">1 Chr. 15. 15.</note> blamed and puniſhed for not obſerving order. St. <hi>Paul</hi>
                     <note n="(f)" place="margin">Col. 2. 5.</note> rejoyced, beholding the order of the <hi>Coloſſians;</hi> he<note n="(g)" place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 34.</note> promiſed to ſet things in order at <hi>Corinth;</hi> he charged<note n="(h)" place="margin">Tit. 1. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Titus</hi> to do the ſame at <hi>Creet;</hi> and himſelf was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded publickly to declare at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> his walking accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to<note n="(i)" place="margin">Act. 21. 24.</note> order.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. In the great book of nature there is order; Bees have their Queens, Cranes have their leader, Locuſts their troops; ſo that order is the beauty of Nature, the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Art, and honour of the World.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. From the contrary we may ſee its excellency, ſince where order is not kept,<note n="(1)" place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 33.</note> peace cannot be kept; confuſion and peace agree not.<note n="(2)" place="margin">Job 10. 22.</note> Death is evil, and that is without order; in it are no orderly changes of night, day, heat, cold; nor do men in dying keep order, rich and great men going firſt. But rich and poor, young and old, promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41930:33"/> die without order; and Hell, the worſt of all, hath in it no order; ſurely then it is a kind of death to ſee any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sleidan.</hi> Comment lib. 10. An. 1555.</note> and a kind of Hell to ſee all in diſorder; yea, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular inequality was ſo burdenſom to the ſeditious Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts in their rebellion, that contrary to their doctrine they made one their Captain, another their King, ſo ſeeking to have order, in their hurly-burly diſorders.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Yea, ſuch is the excellency of order, that civil order is the beauty of Kingdoms, ſpiritual of the Church; that the fabrick of the World is upholden by order; that States and Kingdoms are maintained by it, and without it nothing can well flouriſh or proſper. And ſince it hath or ſhould have place in all things, ſurely the Church ſhould not be without it; for order and uniformity in diſcipline is an hedge to unity and doctrine. And where rules for order are deſpiſed, and every man left to himſelf, uſually ſo many Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, ſo many Sects; whereas where all things are done in order, there union in Law, breeds union in love, uniformity in faſhion, uniformity in faith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 3, 4.</p>
                  <p>But alas! where is our order, when as at <hi>Corinth,</hi> ſo with us, one is for <hi>Paul,</hi> another for <hi>Apollo</hi> (and might not any of<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 12</note> theſe have been acceptable and given content?) Sure this is not agreeable to order, ſince St. <hi>Paul</hi> for their ſo doing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 4.</note> ſuch to be carnal; when ſome go to private meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, when they ſhould go to the publique Ordinances; when ſome go to the Lords Table, more keep away than come, ſure it is neither decent, nor according to order.</p>
                  <p>Oh, my beloved brethren, for the Lord's ſake, a God of order, for the Churches ſake, the houſhold of God to be well ordered; live in peace, be of one mind, and obſerve good order. Becauſe many are divided into factions, ſhall we? muſt we needs ſin with others? or becauſe diſorders are abroad, let us unite at home, and be orderly. Order is of God, diſorder is not ſo; ſome muſt begin to make up the breaches, and to quench the flames. Oh that we could be the men! for why ſhould we open the mouths of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, to reproach our Religion, as if in it we had no agreement, no order? why ſhould we tear the Church of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41930:34"/> Chriſt into pieces by our diſorders? why ſhould we be ſtumbling blocks to people, making them at a ſtand, not knowing what to do, whether to be of this, or that, or the other, or of no Religion? why ſhould we deprive our ſelves of that joy, comfort and good, we might receive by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian unity and order?</p>
                  <p>Since therefore God is the Author of good agreement and order, ſince we are all of the ſame family and houſhold of God; ſince we are fellow members of the ſame body, fellow ſtones of the ſame building, and fellow-ſoldiers of the ſame band; ſince we have the ſame Father, God, the ſame Mother, the Church, the ſame enemies, weapons, cauſe, and expect the ſame crown; ſince in Chriſts Kingdom lambs<note place="margin">Iſa. 11. 6.</note> and wolves agree. Labour we for peace, and to uphold in this houſe, in this Kingdom, fold and family, unity and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. In contentions therefore deal like neighbours, in State buſineſs like ſubjects, in other mens ſins like Chriſtians, in all humane things as juſt men; and in all we do be careful to obſerve order.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That all things may be done decently and in order, lay aſide pride, paſſion, prejudice and pragmatical dealing in things out of our Calling; for when meer Mechanicks from the anvile, thimble, needle, yea from tinkering and tapſtering, preſume to ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi> chair, to be dictators and reformers. It is ſure againſt order, and a cauſe of much diſorder.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That all things may be done decently and in order, by no means have a prejudicate opinion againſt the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the Church, I mean the Biſhops, they having been therein, in and ſince the Apoſtles times; St. <hi>James</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> at <hi>Antioch,</hi> St. <hi>Mark</hi> at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> &amp;c. And after them ſuch Worthies of the Church, St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hippo, Chryſoſtom of Conſtantinople, Ambroſe</hi> of <hi>Millain, Cyprian</hi> of <hi>Carthage,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Fulgentius, Palladius</hi> and <hi>Finan,</hi> Biſhops in <hi>Scotland,</hi> before Antichriſt; three<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luther,</hi> pag. 41.</note> Britiſh Biſhops at the famous Councel of <hi>Nice, Ariſtobulu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> one of the ſeventy Diſciples, as we are informed, a Biſhop in <hi>Britain.</hi> And of the nine and twenty Clergy men, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41930:34"/> in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, five were Biſhops, and one Arch-Deacon. Such hath been the Government of the Church in and ſince the Apoſtles time; and if ſome have been faulty, perſonal faults may not annihilate needful functions.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That all things may be done decently and in order, let us better eſteem of things appointed by our Church for unity, edification and order, and not cauſeleſly run into fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and fraternities, ſcandalous to the Goſpel, dangerous to our ſelves.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1</label> Some I know will ſay, to obey and obſerve order in things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by authority, is againſt conſcience.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> That Magiſtrates have power to command is cleer, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. Surely then they may make Laws, they being called powers; ſurely ſuch receive force from God, they being or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God; ſurely ſuch bind, ſince we muſt be ſubject, <hi>v.</hi> 5. and ſurely violaters ſin, ſince reſiſters receive damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>v.</hi> 2.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> But I am perſwaded that ſuch and ſuch particulars are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful?</head>
                     <p n="1">1. If the thing commanded is ſimply unlawful, as to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> the golden image; if the thing it ſelf is lawful, yet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to that lawful thing, to ſome, puts upon a neceſſity of ſinning; as when ſingle life, lawful to ſome, is impoſed to ſuch who have not the gift of continency. If indifferents are commanded as neceſſary, as meritorious, and as the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials of Religion, ſuch commands loſe their force; yet not ſo, but all commands of Magiſtrates wanting authority of the Word, ought not to be diſobeyed with ſcandal and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt: Even Heathen perſecuting Kings had ſuch authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from God, that Chriſtians were to pray for them, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey<note place="margin">1 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 1, 2.</note> them, commanding things lawful actively, commanding things unlawful paſſively.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. You ſay you are perſwaded they are unlawful, this makes them not to be ſo. If there is no rule from the word for their unlawfulneſs, there is no place for your diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but the command to obey is ſufficient warrant to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey. It is a great miſtake to ſwallow Camels ſins, and to ſcruple at matters indifferent (not once pretended to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41930:35"/> the word, they being alſo commanded by authority, and that ſuch we are to obey) upon no better grounds than ſuch, they are contrary to our fancy, humour, opinion, or Chriſtian liberty, as pretended; for Chriſtian liberty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in freedom from ſin, from the curſe of the Law, from the wrath of God, the yoak of Moſaical rites, and an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation<note place="margin">
                           <p>There is a glorious liberty which is celeſtial in heaven, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 21. On earth there is a liberty temporal, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 29. This liberty is beſt when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ffence is neither gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven nor ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. There is a liberty ſpiritual, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. 36. which conſiſts in deliverance from evil, from ſin, from the puniſhment of the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 13. from the ſtrict obſervation of the Law, which ſaith; do and live; freedom in reſpect of God, to have free acceſs to ſerve him in the Name of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 2. To ſerve him without fear, in righteouſneſs and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 74. and freedom in reſpect of the creatures, to uſe or not to uſe our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion loſt by <hi>Adam,</hi> it being reſtored by Chriſt, ſo that all are ours, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 22. all being pure to the pure, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 14. There is alſo a carnal liberty to ſwear, to lye, to ſlander, to ſerve God when and how men liſt, to ſhun Gods Ordinances and publick Meetings; and this is a liberty ſtood for by ſome, whereas this is no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty, but a diſſolute licentiouſneſs; for notwithſtanding our liberty, we muſt pay debts, and perform duties, to whom debts or duties belong.</p>
                           <p>Scripture mentions a good, a cleer, a pure, a purged, a weak, an evil, and a feared conſcience. If the conſcience for which men plead liberty, loves diviſions, which God hates, it is but a bad conſcience.</p>
                        </note> of conſcience to the things indifferent, as ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als. As for liberty of conſcience, ſo much deſired of ſome, who know not what they deſire, I could ſhew how <hi>John Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cold, Nicholas Stock, Mancer</hi> and others pleaded for, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the deſired liberty; but having power in their hands, they would not grant the ſame to others. And ſure we may remember, how ſome would not grant it to others, who are now moſt deſirous of it themſelves. But who I pray ſhould have liberty of conſcience? Sure I am, it is not agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by thoſe who have written earneſtly for the ſame. Some would have it granted to all conſcientious men only; but who are they? ſome not to ſuch who ſin againſt the light of nature, and reaſon, and here will be ſome doubt. And ſome would have it granted to all men, in all Nations; whereas if to all, what confuſion? if to ſome only, what diſſenſion?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <p>Concerning things indifferent, as ſuch things are which I may lawfully do, or uſe, as I may forbear from, or drink wine, ale, beer, or water; I may cloath my ſelf with wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len or linnen, I may uſe the geſtures of ſitting, ſtanding, kneeling, ſo long as I am at liberty; for a Chriſtian is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41930:35"/> to moderate his liberty in the uſe of things indifferent, of which there are two chief moderators.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. General, namely, charity, directing us when and where to uſe our liberty (the thing being indifferent to us) this made St. <hi>Paul</hi> to ſay, he would eat no fleſh whilſt the world ſtood, rather than offend his brother.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Special, as lawful authority abridging a man of this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. For example; It is indifferent for a man to take to, and follow this or that trade, yet the Magiſtrate for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good limits this liberty ſo, that no man ſhall follow ſuch a Trade until he have ſerved ſuch a time, nor in a corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, except or until he be free of the ſame. For Merchants to tranſport commodities is indifferent. The Magiſtrate for publick good limits this liberty, and forbids the tranſporting of ſome things for a certain time. To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ate fiſh, fowl, or fleſh is indifferent. The Magiſtrate limits ſo as before.<note place="margin">See the rubricks after the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion for kneeling at it.</note> And whereas it is lawful to pray ſtanding or kneeling, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Communion ſitting, ſtanding or kneeling, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to maintain uniformity and order, moderates and limits this liberty, appointing all in publick prayer, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the communion, to uſe the geſture of kneeling, as moſt decent, orderly, religious, and tending to uniformity; which determinations of authority are to be obeyed becauſe<note place="margin">There is a certain <hi>ignoto</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, they ſay, who affirms, that if the Magiſtrate enjoyns, liberty is loſt. And when we reply, grant that and confuſion will follow in families, in Kingdoms. To this, this <hi>Ignaro</hi> anſwers; in civil and temporal matters the Magiſtrate may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and we lawfully obey, not in Eccleſiaſtical and religious; but alas, this piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſingle <hi>umbra</hi> either knows not or fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>gets, that the actions of Gods worſhip are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eſſential or circumſtantial; eſſential are principal, as piety, holineſs, or ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate, as helps to the better performing and declaring of ſuch worſhip, as prayer preaching, Sacraments, concerning which we may conſider, That they, as prayer, preaching, Sacraments, are neceſſarily to be performed, becauſe inſtituted of God. 2. Circumnantia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, which ſhew the manner how they are to be performed, concerning the place, time, geſture, &amp;c. theſe are left to the Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 24. St. <hi>Paul</hi> would order ſuch things when he came, and ſaw what was convenient, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 29. the Church then enjoyned things long ſince abrogated. <hi>Titus</hi> muſt order things in <hi>Creet,</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> enjoyns, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. to ſubmit to every Ordinance of man; ſubmit therefore, honour, pay all duties; to every humane Ordinance, humane be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe proper to men, and by ſome humane act, for the Lords ſake, namely, under God, of God, from God; to every, to all Governours, good and bad, in all things which do not croſs Piety and Religion; our obedience is to go ſo far as their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion is to command; not to civil cauſes only, but to religious alſo; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their precepts may not be followed, our obedience muſt be paſſive. But whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever lawful thing is appointed by the Church, for order and decency, may with a good conſcience, yea ought to be obeyed.</note> lawful and commanded. And I deſire ſuch who think the command of a lawful thing makes it unlawful, to apply it to your own occaſions, as after this manner; your man may, yea he ought, it is his duty to ſaddle your horſe, and do any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch thing; but in caſe you bid him do it, then your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand makes it unlawful. Apply it thus to your ſelves, and you will ſee the fondneſs of ſuch fancies.</p>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:41930:36"/>
                     <p> The old Non-Conformiſts in their modeſt confutation of Separatiſts, anſwering their objections concerning uſing ſtinted commanded prayers, ſay, The peoples underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and memory is better helped by that they are acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with, than with other, pag. 14. And that it is lawful to uſe ſuch good forms which are impoſed by authority—And we ought the rather to do good things that are agreeable to the Word, when we know them to be alſo commanded by the Chriſtian Magiſtrate, pag. 15.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1</label> But by ſo doing we ſhall offend our weak brother, which we are forbidden to do.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> All are not weak in their own opinions who plead for ſuch.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Weak are to be informed, not to be nouriſhed in their weakneſs, and wilful are to be oppoſed.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. By obeying you ſhall offend ſome, by diſobeying you ſhall offend many; by obeying you will offend ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſons, by diſobeying you ſhall offend publick. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are we to prefer the few or many, the private or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> Chriſt condemns the traditions of men, Mat. <hi>15. 9.</hi>Things enjoyned are ſuch.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> Chriſt condemns thoſe of the Phariſees, for they were enjoyned as parts of God's Worſhip, contrary to God's commandments, and preferred before them, and upon opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of merits by them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 6. as neceſſary to ſalvation.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41930:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> Ours are not ſo, but only for decency, common order and uniformity.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>3</label> But I think others to be better, and ſuch to be needleſs.</head>
                     <p n="1">
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> 1. Some muſt determine, elſe ſo many men, ſo many minds, ſo many wayes.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. They who determine cannot, may not be every one; but ſuch whom God hath ſet over us.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. And admit ſome things in our conceits might be amended; is not peace better than contention about them, they being lawful? who in his wits will pull down a fair building, becauſe he thinks a tyle doth not lye well to his mind?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>4</label> But ſuch and ſuch are ſuperſtitious.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> Many talk much of ſuperſtition, and againſt it, who know not what it is, and themſelves in refuſing ſome things, are oftentimes more ſuperſtitious. Superſtition properly taken, is too much ſtrictneſs about extremity in Religion, and it is<note place="margin">
                           <p>It is <hi>meti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culoſus nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor,</hi> as <hi>Theophrast</hi> hath it in his chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters; or as others, <hi>Nimia cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca ſacra Religio.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Superſtitioſum eſt quicquid institutum eſt ab hominibus, ad ſacienda &amp; colenda idola pertinens, vel ad colendam ſicut Deum creaturam partem ve ullam creaturae vel ad conſultationes, &amp; pacta cum daemonibus, &amp;c. Decretal.</hi> 2. <hi>p. cauſ.</hi> 26. <hi>q.</hi> 2. <hi>c. illud.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </note> ſometimes joyned with idolatry, <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 22. They were more ſuperſtitious than others, worſhipping more Heathen God's than others, or were more devout in Heathen Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip than others. Take ſuperſtition for a nimity or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muchneſs in the inward and ſubſtantial parts of Religion, ſo no man can be ſuperſtitious, namely, too much truly religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; no man can pray to the true God too fervently, or hear his Word too reverently or attentively.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                        </label> But is it not ſuperſtition to aſcribe holineſs to times, places, and things?</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> Ignorance will fault things cauſeleſly; for no more is meant, than that ſuch are ſet apart from common to holy uſes.</p>
                     <p>But we are to know that ſuperſtition may be as well in placing piety in the Negative as Affirmative, in not kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as kneeling; in abſtaining ſcrupulouſly from things
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:41930:37"/> commanded, as in uſing them ſcrupulouſly. Negative pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts are as perfect in forbidding things unlawful, as affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in requiring things neceſſary, or permitting things law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. If it is ſuperſtition when men not contented with the preſcribed manner of worſhip, gather together an heap needleſly; then when men beyond Gods reſtraint, increaſe reſtraints upon themſelves or others to pleaſe God, they are thereby ſuperſtitious in the Negative. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 21. forbids will-worſhip in Negative obſervances; <hi>Touch not, taſte not, handle not.</hi> They therefore who add reſtraints where God hath not, in ſo doing may be negatively ſuperſtitious, as the Phariſees in not doing ſome things on the Sabbath day; and the Philiſtines not treading upon the threſhold of Dagon. In abſtaining therefore from things lawful, as unlawful, there may be a negative ſuperſtition. There is then a ſuperſtition poſitive and negative; the one, when men count that holy which God never made holy; the other, when men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn that which God never condemned, both faulty. It is not for us to make ſins or duties. To make more ſins than God made, is a condemning of the rule as imperfect, as if the Law was not full and exact enough, but needed to be pieced up by mens fancies; yet ſo do ſome, who upon their own will and ſenſe, without any warrant from the Word, condemn men for uſing things indifferent, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. no where forbidden, and by authority commanded. Take heed, take heed that our hatred of ſuperſtition make us not mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, like ſome modern Antitrinitarians, who reject the doctrine of the Trinity becauſe the Pope holds it, or ſuch who will meddle with nothing which in Popery was polluted.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <p>If things enjoyned be not ſinful like theirs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 9. if they are of things neceſſary or uſeful for the time, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 28. ſuch do bind the conſcience, and are no violation of it. Chriſtian liberty, a freedom from the tyranny of ſin, the curſe of the Law, the yoak of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the like as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is a great liberty, which may content, and a precious thing to ſtand faſt in, but we muſt not turn it to licenſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 13. Although we are free, yet we muſt not uſe our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty<note place="margin">Gal. 5. 1.</note>
                        <pb n="65" facs="tcp:41930:37"/> as a cloak of maliciouſneſs, but know we are ſtill the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, and owe him obedience, and to every one of<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 16</note> his commandments, whereof this is one; ſubmit to every<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 13.</note> humane Ordinance for the Lords ſake, and by love bound to ſerve one another, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 13.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. Conſider the frequent and peremptory charge of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, of obedience, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13.</item>
                        <item>2. Conſider that to deſpiſe dominion is very dangerous, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 10. <hi>Jude</hi> 8.</item>
                        <item>3. That vain janglings about indifferents have much ſcandalized the Goſpel of Chriſt.</item>
                        <item>4. And hazarded the loſs of God's Ordinances, and made many deprive themſelves wofully of them.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p n="3">3. Thirdly, Muſt all things be done decently and in order?</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Then you muſt have a Teacher, elſe where is order? In an houſe, no Steward or Governour; in a War, no Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rector, ſure no order.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. This Teacher muſt not be any one, not every one; that was <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s ſin, and of later times a cauſe of much, of many and ſad diſorders.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. This Teacher muſt have maintenance fitting to his function; ſo that feeding the Flock, he may eat of the milk of the flock; for when ſuch are contemned in regard of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, when in regard of it they are ſcorned, when there is a ragged Miniſter, and a rich people, what decency? what or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</p>
                     <p n="4">4. This Preacher and people muſt conſider they are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of a Church, and ſubject to its government, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in all things they are to ſubmit and obey its lawful Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and injunctions. For inſtance,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Our Church enjoyns us to come at the beginning, and ſtay until the end of the publick Worſhip of God; and this is agreeable to Scripture, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 46. 10. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 21.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The Church enjoyns us to pray kneeling, which is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Scripture precept, and the practiſe of the beſt men, as <hi>David, Solomon, Paul,</hi> and our Saviour Chriſt; yet we have ſome who at the publick prayers of the Church, will not<note place="margin">Pſal. 95. 6.</note>
                        <pb n="66" facs="tcp:41930:38"/> ſtand with the Phariſee, nor kneel with the Apoſtle; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtand as ſervants to a Maſter, nor kneel as ſubjects be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Prince, but ſit as if they were to bleſs God, not he them; much leſs imitate thoſe who with wives and children, and as is moſt probable (being they paſſed through the City) in their better apparel, and yet in prayer would kneel, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in a moſt incommodious place, to wit, the Sea-ſhore.<note place="margin">Act. 21. 5.</note> Sure it argues ignorance or arrogance to refuſe to kneel in prayer to God, in which duty no geſture ſo fitting as kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; if poſſible, if not injurious, if not hindering edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The Church enjoynes men to be uncovered in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God; and there is no doubt but that we may teſtifie our reverence to God, as we do to men; nor do I know of any Church where the Miniſter is uncovered, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple covered (too much in uſe with us) he being there as God's Embaſſador, the people as they to whom he is ſent; he as a Teacher, they to learn. Give me leave to tell you what an eminent Divine ſaith. <hi>He who thinks</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>he may not be uncovered out of fear to offend God, may be ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Nicol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon's</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Mr. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thews,</hi> pag. 187.</note> 
                        <hi>yea, whilſt he ſpeaks againſt all ceremonies, is ceremonious; and he that thinks upon no occaſion he may cover his head, is cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious alſo; and yet for his ſuperſtition he hath a fairer excuſe than the other; for the one doth it for the most part out of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and perverſeneſs, and in a diſobedience to ſome higher power; the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ut of a kind of neceſſity, which his preſent condition may put him upon (and 'tis a certain rule, charity diſpenceth with all ceremonies.) The one by it may give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ccaſion to ſuſpect his irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; the worſt that can be made of the other, is that he deſires to ſerve his God with fear and reverence, as judging himſelf in his preſence, before whom he cannot be t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o vile. The one hath no coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r colour of any Scripture for what he d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>es, the other looks upon theſe plain words of the Apoſtle,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 4. <hi>and thinks he is obliged to it, as indeed he is, till the meaning of the Text <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e otherwiſe cleered to him. The one is diſobedient to higher powers, the other obedient to the ſame as he ought; better grounds by far than the other, who will do, or not do, becauſe he will, or he will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>uſe ſuch and ſuch do ſo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:41930:38"/> 4. The Church enjoyns all Communicants to receive the Communion three times in the year, of which <hi>Eaſter</hi> to be one. A duty of order, yea more; for if not comers to the Paſſeover were to be cut off, ſurely God who was ſo ſevere<note place="margin">Num. 6. 9, 13.</note> for the neglect of that Sacrament (inferior to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion) how ſevere will he be think we to the contemners of this ſo ſacred an Ordinance? Since alſo not to come is a diſobedience to Chriſt's command <hi>(Do this)</hi> which is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine. And 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 23. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I have received of the Lord that which I delivered unto you.</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 26. <hi>As often as ye eat this bread, and drink this cup:</hi> Which <hi>as often,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies often, as the Apoſtles and primitive Chriſtians under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood it; yea, and the not comers neglect the memory of Chriſts death (by which we are redeemed) in his way. They neglect alſo the communication of Chriſt's body and blood, and ſhew themſelves none of Chriſt's Diſciples, not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him (his Sheep hearing his voice) in this; nor imitating him (whom we are to follow) who did eat the Paſſeover, a type of his Paſſion, as to put an end to it, ſo to honour his Ordinance, and to ſhew us our duty, what we are to do; to ſhew his ſubjection to the Law, as our pattern and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</p>
                     <p>But alas! what are we come unto? whither ſhall we go? If in ſome places where are hundreds of families, and not one hundred to communicate; if ſome who are married, if ſome of thirty, if not forty years of age were never at the Communion; if in populous places and Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the moſt turn their backs upon this Ordinance. Is this for edification? is this order?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1</label> I dare not come ſaith one, leſt I come unworthily.</head>
                     <p n="1">
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> 1. And why will you come unworthily? why will you prefer your ſinful luſts before Chriſt and ſalvation? Repent, amend.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To come unworthily is ſinful, not to come may be as great, if not a greater ſin. He who comes doth what he is enjoyned (although he fail in the manner) and ſo may ſhew a neglect; the other who comes not, ſhews contempt of Chriſt's command, <hi>Do this;</hi> ſo contempt of the memory of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41930:39"/> Chriſt's death, by which we are redeemed; and ſhews him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf none of Chriſt's Diſciple, and ſurely contemners ſin fearfully. To neglect to come therefore is a groſs ſin, where a man in coming as well prepared as he can, he doth his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and humbly commits himſelf unto God's mercy.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> I cannot come ſaith another, becauſe of the company, many being admitted to come who are bad, and with ſuch St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith I muſt not eat; and if I may not eat with them, then not come to the<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 9, 10, 11, 12.</note> Lords Table with them.</head>
                     <p n="1">
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> 1. I may not be his familiar, his companion, therefore I may not communicate with him, not go to the Church with him, is weak and frivolous; for to eat at home is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different action, left to my choice, and I may not chuſe evil. To eat at the Sacrament is part of Gods ſervice, not to be omitted without ſin, it being his and my duty. Although I muſt ſeparate from him in civil familiarity, which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and unneceſſary where I have liberty (not elſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 13, 14.) yet I may not in ſacred ſociety, and the ſervice of God, which is his duty and mine, if he be not caſt out of the Church by excommunication. As I am to avoid the leaſt partaking of other mens ſins, ſo am I bound to the greateſt partaking with them in duty; and yet I may eat with him, if occaſionally I be caſt upon the ſame Inn, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, and Table, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Scriptures enjoyning ſeparation from wicked men, command to depart or ſeparate from their ill courſes, their ſins, not from being with them in Gods Ordinances. Should a ſick man ſay I will not accompany ſuch who are ſick to a Phyſician, and be healed; is he not guilty of his own death for ſo doing?</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Sure it is an error to imagine that communicating with wicked men is a ſin in the worthy Communicant, or a being polluted by their company, ſince the keeping company with them in ſuch ſacred meetings, is only an acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that they are in the number of them whom Chriſt came to redeem; and ſo ſaith St. <hi>Peter.</hi> It is only a joyning with<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 1.</note> them in Chriſtian profeſſion, and a confederating with them to lead Chriſtian lives; all which are Chriſtian acts and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:41930:39"/> tokens of humility, unlike the Phariſee, who condemned and triumphed over the Publican; whereas it would be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to look more at home to our own wayes and works, and leave judging of others, than to deprive our ſelves of ſo ſacred an Ordinance for other mens coming, ſince St. <hi>Paul</hi> reproves not the giver, nor the worthy receiver at <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> only the unworthy comer; ſince upon ſuch grounds of ſeparation, there will be no reſting; and ſince to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, becauſe of other mens unworthineſs, is a new-found groundleſs fancy; not in our Saviours time, when <hi>Judas</hi> came, nor in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> time, when many came unworthy, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>3</label> We cannot touch pitch and not be defiled; we encourage them in their ſins by our preſence, whom we muſt reprove.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> It hath already been ſhewed, that it defileth not to do a good duty with a ſinful man, as the Phariſee did not ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to go to the Temple with the Publican, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>4</label> But we cannot communicate with that Church which hath no diſcipline.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> Diſcipline there is, although perhaps not of that kind which ſome deſire; yet ſuch, as the Church hath ſtood and flouriſhed under, ſince the Apoſtles time, until the laſt Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury. And ſuch as hath made as good Chriſtians in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and as zealous Martyrs as any in the world. And if this diſcipline be not executed, it is the ſin of thoſe unto whom<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Auguſtin. cont. par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>n. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> it is committed, unleſs as it often happens, the multitude of offendors, or the difficulty of the times impede the ſame.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>5</label> We would come might we receive it as we would.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> You would obey, might you diſobey; and your diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (doing as you liſt) go for obedience.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>6</label> Oh no, We deſire to receive in a Goſpel way, in which we may imitate Chriſt, which we do not if we kneel.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> Very good, you deſire to imitate Chriſt, then kneel; for we who do kneel deſire to and do imitate Chriſt; for our Saviour at the Paſſeover did conform to the Paſſeover ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture enjoyned by, and practiſed in the Church wherein he lived; we therefore kneeling according to the practiſe of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41930:40"/> the Church wherein we live, do imitate Chriſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>7</label> What Chriſt did we muſt do.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> Prove that Chriſt did not kneel, and that he forbad us to kneel. That Chriſt did ſit, and commanded us to ſit, and we<note place="margin">
                           <p>He did ſit; what Chriſt did not do, we muſt not do. He did not kneel, what Chriſt did we muſt do. Whoſo reads ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, will not take Chriſts example as a rule to guide the Church in all circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in adminiſtring and delivering the Euchariſt; for muſt we deliver it upon Maunday Thurſday, in a chamber, not in a Church, only to twelve at once, thoſe only men, and Clergy men? Muſt we deliver it to them lying or leaning upon one anothers boſom, not in the morning but at night, not faſting but after ſupper; and muſt the deliverer waſh the receivers feet?</p>
                           <p n="2">2. Chriſt did not make his example our pattern in ſuch circumſtances of time, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants geſture, &amp;c. but left his to be guided by his Church in all matters of come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and order. We read of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> ſetting things in order, yea ſeeming to croſs the order of Chriſt, forbidding the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to ſup before, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 21. And the Church in St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> time did receive the Communion faſting, Epiſt. 18. Chap. 6. he ſaith the whole Church, the world over, received it faſting; that Chriſt left the manner of receiving to the Apoſtles, that they appointed it to be received faſting, and that the altering of the receiving of it after ſupper to take it faſting, was the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the holy Ghoſt; for the honour of the Sacrament, to have it enter before any external meat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </p>
                           <p>Object. <hi>Chriſt did ſit,</hi> Mat. 26. 20.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt did not ſit as we do; but according to the cuſtom of thoſe Eaſtern Countreys, did adminiſter, as the Paſſeover, ſo his Supper, lying on the floor upon couches, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 1. 6. Mr. <hi>Beza</hi> from <hi>Joſephus</hi> concludes, that they did lye upon couches, that one lay upon his next fellow, with their feet laid outward. And the Greek word ſhews as much, <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, Mat. 26. 20. Macc. 14. 18. Joh. 13. 23. <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, ſignifying to ſit upon a bed, to take meat after the ancient cuſtom. And in <hi>Luk.</hi> 22 14. <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, ſignifying to lye along, to lye down. The poſture was therefore leaning or lying along, not ſitting; beſides, the geſture was changed from God's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 11.</p>
                           <p>Obj. <hi>What Chriſt did not, we muſt not do. Chriſt did not kneel, therefore we may not.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt did not give it in the morning, nor to Lay-men, to no women, not in a Church. Chriſt did not give, nor the Apoſtles receive it ſtanding nor ſitting, as not kneeling, therefore he left ſuch particulars to the wiſdom of the Church to order.</p>
                        </note> are agreed, ſince what Chriſt did and commanded us to do, we muſt do.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. What Chriſt did not we muſt not do; what, not bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize? not communicate with women? What Chriſt did we muſt do; what, take after Supper? with a Lamb? only with twelve?</p>
                     <p n="3">3: Some things Chriſt did as God, ſome as Mediator, ſome as man; and as man he did many things neceſſary for us to follow him; and he did ſome actions as man indifferent, left free, not for our imitaion.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:41930:40"/> 4. Churches who underſtand the duty and geſtures uſed by Chriſt, better than ſuch objectors, leave all Churches to their liberty (not particular members in them to theirs) and hence it is that ſome take it ſtanding, ſome kneeling, and ſome as the Church of <hi>Poland,</hi> either ſtanding or kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but not allowing ſitting, becauſe the wicked <hi>Arrians</hi> receive it ſitting, as implying their equality with Chriſt as man, or at leaſt derogatory from his divinity as God. Our Rubrick ſhews there is no adoration of the Elements; and it is manifeſt that adoration came not in amongſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, until after Tranſubſtantiation, which came in about 1215. and adoration about 1226. nor did <hi>Honorius</hi> appoint adoration to be uſed in the act of receiving, but at the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and when carried about. I pray ſuppoſe a Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor may have his pardon ſealed, with many priviledges to boot, provided he will take it upon his knees, not elſe, and he will rather die than take it ſo, becauſe ſome take it on horſe-back, others ſitting, would not men condemn his ſtubbornne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s, and ſay he juſtly periſhed? Apply it I pray.</p>
                     <p>Oh my beloved brethren, ſhall we deprive our ſelves of this ſign to preſent, this ſeal to confirm, and this means to convey Chriſt and his benefits to us, for we know not what, for an harmleſs geſture, ſavouring of humility in our ſelves, and obedience to Governours, which Mr. <hi>Beza</hi> calls a ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 12. <hi>opuſc. tom.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>0</note> of holy Chriſtian adoration. Is this our thankfulneſs to God for planting us in the moſt flouriſhing Church in the world? Is this our reſpect we bear to our firſt Reformers, who ſealed the Reformation with their blood, and to ſuch who have happily defended it? Is this the care and love we have to our ſelves, to quarrel at and deprive our ſelves of God's Ordinances for an harmleſs geſture? Is the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion a badge of Chriſtianity, and ſhall we be aſhamed of Chriſtianity, ſo of Chriſt? Is it a means to feed and nouriſh our ſouls ſpiritually, and ſhall we ſlight it as not needing ſuch nouriſhment? Are we to receive, to teſtifie our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs for the death of Chriſt, for which we can never be ſufficiently thankful, and ſhall we think much to do it? Is
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:41930:41"/> our coming to the Lord's Table to teſtifie our Communion with God, with Chriſt, with his Spirit and Church, and to increaſe the ſame, that we may live more in unity, love and concord, and ſhall we neglect it?</p>
                     <p n="5">5. The Church enjoyns all to come to the prayers of the Church, decently and in order. And this is agreeable to all reformed Churches who have their forms. To the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Church of the <hi>Jews,</hi> meeting ſolemnly at their hours of prayers, and to the directions of God, <hi>Numb.</hi> 6. 23. <hi>Deut.</hi> 26. 3, 5. Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> hath his reaſons for ſet forms in publick; an help for the weak, to keep uniformity, &amp;c.<note place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae.</note> yet alas, we have with us who ſay, they are abominable, ſtumbling blocks, walking with crutches, &amp;c. yet ſuch were appointed by God and our Saviour, and uſed by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles. Conſider whether is better, to pray with conſideration or without? whether he doth beſt who deliberates, or he who doth not? whether we can pray be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than Scripture prayers? Although we may enlarge and vary them, to make them more particular and pertinent to our perſonal occaſions. Whether he who prayes devoutly the Lord's prayer, doth not pray with the Spirit, ſince Chriſts Spirit taught it? whether it is not as fit to offer <hi>ex tempore</hi> preaching to the people, as <hi>ex tempore</hi> prayer to God?<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Durel,</hi> pag. 64, 184.</note> And as for the prayers of our Church, we have the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the Reformed Churches. And I have read, that <hi>Gilbertus</hi> a <hi>German</hi> propounds ours for a ſample of the forms of the ancient Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ch. We have alſo the approbation of an Army of Martyrs. Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> in a Sermon affirms, that the ſervice ſet forth by King <hi>Edward</hi> was good, becauſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God's Word, and the order of the primitive Church. Dr. <hi>Tayler</hi> ſaith, that that book was ſo fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected according to the Rules of Chriſtian Religion, that no Criſtian conſcience could be offended with any thing therein contained. Biſhop <hi>Ridley</hi> a little before his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom, hearing that Mr. <hi>Knox</hi> did fault the Common-Prayer-Book, ſaid; Alas, that brother <hi>Knox</hi> could not bear with our Common-Prayer; a man of parts and wit as he is, may produce popular arguments againſt it, yet I ſuppoſe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:41930:41"/> he cannot be able ſoundly by the Word of God to diſprove any part of it. When he who was called Protector ſent a command to look to Ale-houſes, and Readers of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer, Mr. <hi>Gatford,</hi> ſince Doctor of Divinity, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred Divine, ſent to him and his Parliament-Houſe a tart rebuke in print for joyning the Common-Prayer with Ale-houſes, and a bold challenge, requeſting that all might be commanded to object what they could againſt it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing that he and ſome few of his ſequeſtred Brethren would make good: That that Book is abſolutely the beſt and freeſt from exception that ever ſaw light in the Chriſtian world; and that it is none of the weakeſt forts the Church hath againſt Popery and Errors. <hi>John Careleſſe</hi> in his exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation before Dr. <hi>Martin</hi> (it is only in the firſt Edition of the Book of Martyrs, which is in one volume) ſaith, That ſame Book which is ſo conſonant and agreeable to the Word of God, being ſet forth by common authority, both of the King that dead is <hi>(Edward</hi> 6.) and of the whole Parliament-Houſe, ought not to be deſpiſed by me or any other private man, under pain of Gods curſe, high diſpleaſure and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation except they repent.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                        </label> It is Popery.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> Dr. <hi>Weſton</hi> Prolocutor in the Convocation houſe in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> reign, made a bitter invective againſt it. In whoſe reign alſo Papiſts articled againſt ſome of the Martyrs for uſing of it; for being preſent when it was uſed, Arch-Biſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> affirmed, that he with <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> and ſome few more would defend the Book of Common-Prayer againſt all Papiſts in the world (for of a long time they only were the oppoſers of it) and Papiſts now ſo abhor it, that they are to (and will) loſe two parts of three of their rents rather than hear it, and yet Popery? Fie, beſides, what one Popiſh thing is in it? Is there prayer to Saints or Angels? Is there prayer to the dead, or in an unknown tongue? Is there any allowance of Purgatory, of Merit? Is it not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected againſt all the material points of Popery, ſo that if it was obſerved, it was impoſſible Popery ſhould come into <hi>England.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <pb n="74" facs="tcp:41930:42"/>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                        </label> Something in it is in the Maſs-Book, it was taken out of it.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> Is the Lord's Prayer Popery, becauſe it is in the Maſs-Book? Kneeling to <hi>Jupiter</hi> was unlawful; to God is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. St. <hi>Paul</hi> borrowed of Pagans, <hi>Act.</hi> 12. 28. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 12. The Pope defends the Trinity, ſhall we therefore deny it? The Devils and Pagans believe on God, ſo do we.</p>
                     <p>There hath not been, nor can be a greater cauſe of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph to the Papiſts, nor cleerer vindication of their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency in ſuffering ſo much in their eſtates for abſenting themſelves from our ſervice, than ſuch doings of ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, who make the uſe of that ſervice ſcandalous, and ſo great a crime: Upon this advantage given, what may the Papiſts ſay? how may they plead? I pray judge and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And take heed leſt in calling that Popery which is not, you bring it in, by taking away ſuch Bull-warks which ſhould keep it out. And I beſeech you brethren do not flatter your ſelves, by ſaying, the Martyrs had not ſuch gifts as you, nor ſuch lights as you have.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. As for gifts, they were ſo gifted as to ſeal the Goſpel<note place="margin">
                           <p>Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> Preface to the Works of Mr. <hi>Tyndal,</hi> ſaith, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing of learning, of Tongues, and Sciences, with quickneſs of wit in youth, and others doth marvellouſly ſhoot up, as it is to be ſeen to the ſufficient furniſhing of Chriſts Church; yet ſo it happeneth, I cannot tell how, the farther I look back into thoſe former times of <hi>Tyndal, Frith,</hi> and other like, more ſimplicity, with true zeal, with humble modeſty I ſee, with leſs corruption of affections in them—In opening of Scriptures, what truth, what ſoundneſs can a man require more, or what more is to be ſaid than is found in <hi>Tyndal,</hi> &amp;c. The ſame is the judgment of the Learned and witty Prefacer to the Treatiſe, called the Book-Fiſh, (containing certain Treatiſes of <hi>John Frith</hi> the Martyr, taken out of a Cod-fiſhes belly in <hi>Cambridge</hi> Market, <hi>Anno</hi> 1626. and after publiſhed. The Author of that notable Preface is thought to have been Dr. <hi>Thomas Goad</hi> of <hi>Haddenham,</hi> one of our five Divines that were at the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod of <hi>Dort.</hi> This Author ſaith alſo, He knows not how, but he finds a better ſpirit, more vivacity, and efficacy in the writings of the firſt Reformers, than in the more accurate labours of theſe of our times.</p>
                           <p>For new lights, hear the judgment of the old Non-Conformiſts. Opinions now embraced as new truths and lights, are no other for ſubſtance, but the old errors and dotages of <hi>Barrow</hi> and <hi>Greenwood</hi> long ſince publiſhed by them, and by the godly oppoſed; ſo that like ruſty weapons they are newly furbiſhed, and being but the ſame metals and materials, are caſt into a new mold, with an addition of ſome things more of the ſame ſort.</p>
                        </note> with their blood, as to confute their adverſaries, and defend the truth. And Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Hadley</hi> (a Town of Tradeſmen, where Dr. <hi>Tayler</hi> (that great admirer of, and commender of the Book of Common-Prayer) lived, was like an Univerſity for knowledge.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <pb n="75" facs="tcp:41930:42"/> 2. And as for your new lights. Did S. <hi>Paul</hi> hold nothing back, but declare all the counſel of God? <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 27. Did he pronounce him accurſed who preached any other doctrine? <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 8. and command <hi>Timothy</hi> to keep the commandement until Chriſt's appearing, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 14. and muſt we now look for new lights? I cannot imagine that the holy Ghoſt ſhould give <hi>Timothy</hi> as ſolemn a charge as was ever given to mortal man, to obſerve the rules given, until Chriſts coming, and new lights to be expected; yet many pretend much to new lights, and new wayes, and gaze upon them; ſo that as ſome gazing upon <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> loſe their way, and fall into ditches; ſo theſe men ſtare ſo much upon their new lights, that they cannot find the way to God's houſe; and they loſe the true light which hath ſhined, and doth in the Church of God. But whence come theſe new lights? If from Scripture we had them before; if not from Scripture, they are falſe and deceitful lights. Great is the wantonneſs of many, in greet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing new opinions and Opinioniſts, as if former truths were ſapleſs, yet truth is alwayes flouriſhing, although too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are even ſick of new opinions. The Fryars had formed a new Goſpel, and called it the everlaſting Goſpel, they cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it up to be worthier than the Goſpel of Chriſt, as much as the Sun is more perfect than the Moon, the kernel than the ſhell; this continued about thirty years with little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof; it was openly read and expounded in <hi>Paris,</hi> 1235. but 1256. it was oppoſed by the <hi>Pariſian</hi> Doctors, and burnt; as <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> is a vaniſhing Meteor; ſo theſe new lights will I believe vaniſh and fade, as did the Fryars <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ium aeternum.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <p n="6">6. The Church enjoyns God-fathers and God-mothers at Infant-baptiſm. They are at <hi>Geneva.</hi> They are commended by Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> in his caſes of conſcience, and they were conſtantly in the primitive times. <hi>Tertullian</hi> mentions them as agreeable to the cuſtom of the Church; in which cuſtom there is nothing evil, or diſhoneſt; it proceeds from charity,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41930:43"/> it makes for the edification of the Church, and it tends to the profit of the child. <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Tremelius</hi> derive it from, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8. 2. But what need we ſeek the beginning of an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſo good, tending to ſo much piety? Infants are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into the faith and boſom of the Church, which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore requires certain perſons, honeſt and pious, to undertake to ſee what is promiſed to be performed, and to take care for the religious education of children; which were it right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerved, how flouriſhing a Church ſhould we have.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1</label> That belongs to Parents, it is their duty.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> It doth. Suppoſe a man oweth an hundred pounds, the debt is his; yet the Creditor for more aſſurance, will have other able men bound, the obligation lyeth on them, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the debt is his: So likewiſe, it is the Parents debt and duty to ſee that the child be religiouſly educated; yet the charity of the Church is ſuch, as to require greater ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, Parents being too often defective. The debt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains the Parents, and there is a tye upon the Sureties.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> This is uſed but as a form or cuſtom.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> The more is the pity, if ſo; and ſo is Religion with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 5. yet is not true Religion at all the worſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>3</label> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ey who are God-fathers and God-mothers do no ſuch duty.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> The charity of the Church is not to be faulted for mens failings. Their negligence is to be lamented, the uſe not to be condemned.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="objection">
                     <head>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>4</label> They who underſtood themſelves, and are conſcious, will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take no ſuch charge imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſible to be kept.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> This is a raſh cenſure, and an ignorant ſlander of the Church, whoſe intention is to have none but knowing and conſcientious perſons, who may and will perform what is promiſed. The charge alſo given to them is of things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, pious, good, and poſſible; neither God nor man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring impoſſibilities, but pious endeavours. The inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution is therefore good, although by ſome peoples care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſsneſs it degenerates into formality, the common bane of ſacred things. Some love to quarrel with that which others do, and like nothing but their own fancies.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <p n="1">
                        <pb n="77" facs="tcp:41930:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> 1. I beſeech you all to take heed you ſtand not againſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,<note place="margin">Applicat.</note> and ſo ſin in diſobeying lawful authority, reproaching<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Peter de Moulin,</hi> Epiſt. 36. quotes <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za,</hi> ſaying many things may, yea and muſt be born with, which are not rightly enjoyned; for ſpiritual liberty lyeth not in the outward act, but in the intention and belief. If a thing in it ſelf be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to us, it muſt neither be obeyed in the act, nor aſſented to in the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and the will. But if the thing be indifferent in it ſelf, and yet ſeem in the j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>dg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment inconvenient, we may and muſt do it, and neither wrong our liberty, nor our conſcience; for in ſuch caſes our actions are limitted, although our conſciences be free; and the ſuperior power may bind us in <hi>ſoro exteriori,</hi> and leave us free in <hi>ſoro interiori,</hi> wherein Chriſtian liberty lyeth; and cites a place in <hi>Calvins</hi> Inſtit. lib. 4. cap 20. Artic. 1. ſpiritual liberty and political bondage will ſtand well together—And let not the conſequence trouble you, as long as the thing commanded is lawful in it ſelf, we are not anſwerable of the conſequence that may follow, but they who command it. And we who move in the orbe of obedience, muſt quietly follow the motions of the high<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r ſphear of authority. To puſh againſt it, inconſiderately under pretence of God's ſervice, is daſhing the ſecond Table againſt the firſt, and breaking both; and cites <hi>Beza,</hi> Epiſt. 24. ſaying, That man abuſeth Chriſtian liberty, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is ſold under ſin, who will not with a free will obey in the Lord his Magiſtrates or Superiors, and ſeeketh not to edifie the conſciences of his Brethren.</note> the Church as if it impoſed things unlawful, diſturbing the peace of the Church, advantaging Papiſts, our diſcords be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their muſick, ſcandalizing the Goſpel, and hindring the edification of our brethren, as they do who think it Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion enough to ſpeak againſt lawful eſtabliſhed order.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. My Brethren of the Clergy, we preach for edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for order. See we, that our ſelves be not diſorderly in our lives. It was ſaid of <hi>Origen</hi> (and may of many more) that his teaching and living were alike. Sure it is a bleſſed thing, when Miniſters lives put not their words to the bluſh, as when much heavenly doctrine ſounds from them in peoples ears, and there is little in the preachers heart; when there is holineſs in the Preachers Books, but none in their boſoms. Preachers ſhould ſhew themſelves patterns of the rules they preſcribe, it being an excellent commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation when Preachers lives are Commentaries of their doctrine; when their exemplary Sermons conſiſt of living words, or words tranſlated into works. For as <hi>Jovinian</hi> the Emperor ſaid to the Orthodox and <hi>Arrian</hi> Biſhops, I cannot judge of your doctrine, but I can judge of your lives; I can
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41930:44"/> ſee who is moſt peaceable and innocent. So we cannot but know, that people can better judge of our doings, than of our doctrine; and are ſooner led to evil by the one, than to good by the other. You know who ſaith, What haſt thou to do to take my Covenant in thy mouth, and hateſt to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed? Thou who teacheſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf? And you know who pronounceth ſuch to be inexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble?<note place="margin">Pſa. 50. 16 Rom. 2. 21 Rom. 2. 1.</note> Sure it will be an heavy ſentence to hear, Out of thine own mouth I will condemn thee; we therefore who preach againſt ſin, ſee we draw not men to ſin by our bad examples; be not we negligent in reading, preaching, catechiſing, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring the Sacraments, &amp;c. Be not we vain and vitious in our lives, but careful to walk decently and in order.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Church-Wardens, you are choſen to reform diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to ſee all things to be done decently and in order; and to bind you hereunto you have an oath, a ſtrong and ſacred tye, yea, ſuch that God will be a ſwift witneſs againſt, &amp; will<note place="margin">Mal. 3. 3. Zech. 5. 4.</note> ſend a curſe to conſume the houſe of the falſe ſwearer. Take heed what you do; If you know in your Pariſhes ſuch who will not come to Communions, to the Prayers of the Church, to nothing done there at all; who will not have their children baptized, nor their children and ſervants ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſed, &amp;c. and you regard not ſuch things; ſurely you are regardleſs of your oaths, and of order.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. And I humbly pray you, by whoſe authority we are here aſſembled, to make it appear that you come hither to have all things done decently and in order. Some (I hope ſlanderouſly) ſay you come hither for money; but I preſume and perſwade my ſelf, you come ſeriouſly to reform mens manners. Some ignorantly ſay, you have no power, you can do nothing. That you have power this meeting ſhews, you calling us hither, and I hope for ſome good end. Let your power and authority I beſeech you be exerciſed as St. <hi>Pauls</hi> was, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 8. for edification; That it may appear we live in a flouriſhing Chriſtian Church, where good Laws are, and they well obſerved and executed; where Religion is profeſſed and practiſed, where the youth are catechiſed, and principeled in Religion; where the Sacraments are duly
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41930:44"/> and orderly adminiſtred, where the houſes of God are ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly frequented, where Schiſms and Factions are diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced, where vice is puniſhed, and vertue encouraged, where mens lives are reformed ſo; that obedience to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, charity and righteouſneſs to men, may and do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and according to this Scripture Canon; all things are done decently and in order.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="postscript">
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:41930:45"/>
                  <head>The POSTSCRIPT.</head>
                  <p>I Reading in Mr. <hi>Howel, Engl.</hi> ſpeaking thus; I that have<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Englands</hi> Tears, pag. 2.</note> been accounted the Queen of Iſles, the darling of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and Neptunes minion; I that have been ſtiled by the character of the firſt Daughter of the Church, that have converted eight ſeveral Nations; I that made the morning beams of Chriſtianity ſhine upon <hi>Scotland,</hi> upon <hi>Ireland,</hi> and a good part of <hi>France;</hi> I that did irradiate <hi>Denmark, Swedland,</hi> and <hi>Norway,</hi> with the light thereof; I that brought the <hi>Saxons,</hi> with other <hi>Germanes</hi> high and low, from Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm to the knowledge of the Coſpel; I that had the firſt Chriſtian King that ever was <hi>(Lucius)</hi> and the firſt reformed King (the eight <hi>Henry)</hi> to reign over me; I out of whoſe bowels ſprung the firſt Chriſtian Emperor that ever was, <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> I that had five ſeveral Kings, <hi>viz. John</hi> King of <hi>France, David</hi> King of <hi>Scotland, Peter</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and two <hi>Iriſh</hi> Kings my captives, in leſs than one year; I under whoſe Banner that great Emperor <hi>Maximilian</hi> took it an honour to ſerve in perſon, and receive pay from me—I that did ſo abound with <hi>Bullion,</hi> &amp;c. Behold, behold I am now become the object of pity to ſome, of ſcorn to others, of laughter to all people, my children abroad are driven to diſavow me for fear of being jeered, they dare not own me their Mother upon the <hi>Rialto</hi> of <hi>Venice,</hi> the <hi>Borle</hi> of <hi>Auſpurge,</hi> the New-bridge of <hi>Paris,</hi> the <hi>Cambios</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> or upon the <hi>Quoys</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi> for fear of being bafled and hooted at, I reading in Mr. <hi>Vines,</hi> what we had been, a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple<note place="margin">His laſt Sermon, <hi>March</hi> 10. 1646.</note> of as powerful godlineſs as any in the world; that practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal divinity was improved to a great height of clearneſs and ſweetneſs, and his lamenting our miſerable declination (in the ſame Sermon) from the life and power of godlineſs,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:41930:45"/> which is come to paſs within theſe few years, ſo that our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticals, our inward and cloſe wayes of walking with God in faith and love, are ſublimed into fancies and vapours, into fumes of new opinions, and which is worſt of all, we take this Dropſie to be growth, and conceive our ſelves more ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual<note place="margin">Page 56.</note> and refined, becauſe more airy and notional. Liberty of Religions is become the golden calf of the times—And<note place="margin">Page 2.</note> the Miniſters are laid low in order to a twofold liberty; the one of propheſying, every one to ſet up Trade who is<note place="margin">Page 23.</note> able; and liberty of luſts and ways of looſeneſs. I conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">In his Faſt Sermon <hi>March</hi> 10 1646.</note> what Mr. <hi>Hodges</hi> ſaith, we have long enjoyed as clear light, and as full diſcoveries of fundamental truths as any Church; others have lighted their Tapers more at our flame, than we at theirs; our Church once the great eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore to Hereticks, envy of Papiſts, refuge of Orthodox, glorious for Doctrine, a praiſe in the earth, the Mother of many Stars of the firſt magnitude, faithful Martyrs, famous Confeſſors, and innumerable ſouls in Heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet after his preaching, in his Epiſtle he ſaith, the Prince of flies hath raiſed ſuch ſwarms of flies in every corner of our Land, that many of our Congregations and Families are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably fly blown with Hereſies, and corrupt Tenets. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mbring ſome paſſages in Sir <hi>Edward Deerings</hi> Speeches<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Octob.</hi> 23. pag. 23.</note> in Parliament, at the beginning of it, ſaying, if we let forth the Government into a loſe liberty for all Religions, we ſhall have none. Libertiniſm will beget Atheiſm,—a little after, Men upon whoſe merit, let my credit ſtand or fall in this Houſe, complain with grief of heart to ſee their now infected ſheep, after long paſtoral, vigilance, and faithful Miniſtery to run and ſtraggle from them more in theſe ten<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nov.</hi> 20. pag. 98.</note> moneths, than in twenty years before;—in another he ſaith, there is at preſent ſuch an all-daring liberty, ſuch a lewd licentiouſneſs, for all mens venting their ſeveral ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (ſenſleſs ſenſes) in Matters of Religion, as never was in any Age, or any Nation until this Parliament was met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Thus the Church of <hi>England,</hi> once the glory of the Reformed Religion is miſerably torn and diſtracted, ſo that you can hardly ſay which is the Church of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:41930:46"/> Theſe ſhew what we have loſt, and what we have found. And I living in the beſt times that ever <hi>England</hi> had, and ſeeing what I ſee, cannot but wiſh with <hi>Jeremy, That my eyes were a</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jer. 9. 1, 2.</note> 
                     <hi>fountain of tears, that I might weep day and night;</hi> for the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and deſtractions in <hi>England;</hi> I now ſeeing the truth of Mr. <hi>Burtons</hi> ſaying, ſuperſtition will run along like a Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Melanch.</hi> pag. 606.</note> in Cattel, ſcab on ſheep, <hi>nulla ſcabies ſuperſtitione ſcabio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſior:</hi> He who is bit of a Mad dog, bites others, and all in the end become mad either out of affection of novelty, ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, blind zeal, hope, &amp; fear the giddy headed multitude will embrace it: So he. <hi>Mahomet</hi> was but a poor Orphan, he<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and. Roſſe</hi> Hiſtory of the World p. 109.</note> marryed his Miſtriſs <hi>Chediga,</hi> whom he made believe, that his falling ſickneſs proceeded from the ſight of Angels which appeared to him: yet he was the beginner of the Mahumetans, which are ſo multiplyed, ſome following <hi>Alli,</hi> ſome <hi>Endocar,</hi> ſome <hi>Acmar,</hi> and ſome <hi>Ozimen,</hi> Mahomets ſucceſſors, whoſe followers are ſubdivided into ſeventy two<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Melanc.</hi> p. 582. Engliſhed by Sir <hi>Rob. Stapelton.</hi>
                     </note> ſorts, as <hi>Leo Affricanus</hi> reports, ſaith Mr. <hi>Burton,</hi> and alſo that <hi>Poland</hi> is a receptacle for all Religions. No marvel then if <hi>Fabianus Strada</hi> calls hereſie the School of Pride, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms that for a man to be an Heretick and a good ſubject is impoſſible, and ſaith, it is with leſs difficulty kept out, than ſhut up. And ſad experience doth fully demonſtrate how errors and hereſies ſwarm amongſt us: ſo that Mr. <hi>Saltm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſh</hi> in his groans for liberty pleads, Whether an hundred and fourſcore Opinions are more to be caſt into the face of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Groans,</hi> p. 13. l. 1. c. 2. p. 15.</note> than ſix hundred in the dayes of <hi>Nazianzen;</hi> and a little after becauſe of our many Opinions and diviſions, he crys out, where is the Church now? not in the Aſſembly (ſaith he) they are but conſulting how to build the Church, not in the Presbytery, for that is a Church unbuilt as yet, not among the Pariſhes, they are not Scripture Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as <hi>Smectymnus</hi> ſaith, where is the Church of <hi>England?</hi> Dr. <hi>Field</hi> of the Church, will tell you Mr. <hi>Saltmarſh,</hi> That there are ſome who profeſs the truth deſcribed by the Son of God, but not wholly and entirely as Hereticks, ſome who profeſs the whole ſaving truth, but not in Unity, as Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks; Some who profeſs the whole truth in unity, not in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:41930:46"/> ſincerity and ſingleneſs of a good and ſanctifyed mind, as hypocrites and wicked men outwardly; Some who profeſs the whole ſaving truth in unity and ſimplicity of a ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and good heart, and I hope you will ſay they are the Church, not excluding the other from the viſible Church, a net, a field <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The old Non-conformiſts in a book ſet forth by Mr. <hi>William Rathband,</hi> will ſhew you that the Church of <hi>England</hi> as formerly eſtabliſhed, was the true Church of Chriſt, and that you ſhould not ſeparate from it. Mr. <hi>Ball</hi> a Non-conformiſt writing againſt <hi>Can</hi> a Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,<note place="margin">Page 75.</note> ſhews you that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is a true Church of Chriſt, a people in Covenant with Chriſt, to whom he hath committed his heavenly Oracles and Seals of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in the ſecond Chapter he ſhews the Church of <hi>England</hi> governed by Biſhops, to be the true Church of<note place="margin">Page 79.</note> Chriſt. Sir <hi>Edward Deering</hi> in one of his Speec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s to the like purpoſe, ſaying, I am bold to forbid any man from this<note place="margin">Page 125.</note> houſe for 1600 years and upward, to name any one age, nay any one year wherein Epiſcopacy was out of date in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom: in another Speech he ſaith, I am none of thoſe men that 1600 years after my Saviour came to plant his Church, will conſent to give a new Rule, a new invented Government to his Church, never known untill this age; yet Mr. <hi>Howel</hi> tells us, that the holy Titles of Biſhops and<note place="margin">Page 138.</note> Prieſts are grown odious amongſt poor Scioliſts, who ſcarce<note place="margin">In his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, p. 5. In Vind. of King ch. 1. p. 49.</note> know the notions of things: And we have amongſt us as Mr. <hi>Symonds</hi> ſaith, ſuch who love ſtrife; and although they have already offered moſt wrong, yet ſtill are moſt full of clamours; and as another ſaith, who cry out much againſt the Pope, to whom they do better ſervice than they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, ſo that he ſaith, it is a thouſand pities that our Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Regum Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cr. Sancto Majeſt.</hi> by J. A.</note> pretending ſuch zeal againſt Popery, who no leſs mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly than confidently rub upon ſound Proteſtants the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſions of Popery and malignancy, do joyn with the worſt of Papiſts, in the worſt at leaſt, in the moſt pernicious Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine<note place="margin">Page 70.</note> of Papiſts. At the beginning of (as in) our troubles His Majeſties Declaration of <hi>Aug.</hi> 12. 1642. ſhews us<note place="margin">Page 18.</note> that nothing was diſcountenanced and reproached, but a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:41930:47"/> regard to us <hi>(i. e.</hi> the King) and our honour, and a ſober eſteem and application to the Laws of the kingdom, and may it not prove ſo again, if not prevented? and ſo be more advantage to run the contrary courſe, if a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. A. <hi>Reg. Sac. San. Maj.</hi> to the Reader.</note> could allow as one ſaith; for if the conforming obedient Clergy muſt lie under the laſh of being prophane and ſcandalous, and the irregular and diſobedient account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and cryed up for the pious, powerful, and precious men, was Mr. <hi>Burton</hi> now alive, he might better ſay than when he wrote thus. What father after a while will be ſo improvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mel.</hi> p. 126.</note> to bring up his ſons to his great charge, to neceſſary beggary? what Chriſtian will be ſo irreligious as to bring up his ſons in that courſe of life which by all probability and neceſſity will entail on him ſymony and perjury, for he might now add ſcorn and contempt if he be an obedient ſon of the Church; for what in regard of pretended conſcience to that Idol Covenant, which <hi>Lil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>urn</hi> calls the make-bate, perſecuting, ſoul-deſtroying, <hi>Englands</hi> dividing, and undo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Engl.</hi> Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, p. 29</note> Covenant? what in regard of the boldneſs of ſome-da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring people; and the connivence of ſome in Authority it had been better for conſcientious ſubjects, that ſome Laws had not been made, than that being made their obedience to them, ſhould be their diſgrace: and the diſobedience of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to them, their honour and dignity. I know that ſome mens natures are eaſieſt cured by lenities, and that if vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence be offered they will ſtruggle, they being eaſier led than driven, but it is not ſo with all, for ſince his Majeſties happy Reſtauration, ſome now daring people began to be tractable and orderly, but feeling the reins of Government ſomewhat looſe, like unruly horſes, they get the bit into their teeth, they kick, and think to run away with, and throw their Rider. Amongſt certain paſſages I have read in the reign of King <hi>James,</hi> this I remember, he who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives<note place="margin">Regum Sacr. Sanc. Majest.</note> me once it is his fault, but if twice it is my fault. What theſe men have done cannot be forgotten, if it is, let <hi>J. A.</hi> remember them, that the beſt of Kings in whom ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice it ſelf, how quick-ſighted ſoever, could not find any thing blame-worthy, except it be a crime to be too good,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:41930:47"/> and tranſcendently clement, forced to flee, his Royal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort neceſſitated to flee beyond ſea, the Royal family divided one from another, his Revenue ſeized, his forts and holds<note place="margin">Curia Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiae.</note> employed to deſtroy him, and another ſpeaking to them thus, you have violated all ſorts of right in the perſon of your King, you have raiſed a war againſt him, you have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten aſſaulted and impriſoned him, you have abuſed the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence<note place="margin">Page 12.</note> he had in you, and deſtroyed him with great cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and inſolency; when ſuch men have acted ſo vigorouſly againſt the Lords anointed, and ſome of them not ſo wary as their fellows ſay, they cannot repent; and are ſuch of whom Mr. <hi>Edw. Sparks</hi> writing of Primitive devotion, ſaith, This<note place="margin">Page 106.</note> ſtolid diſobedient age contemns their devotions, and are ſo<note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e 53.</note> immodeſt as to grudge God the hat &amp; the knee, whatcan we hope for from ſuch men? we may remember the moral of the Country-mans ſnake which would take away life from him who preſerved hers, and not forget that of the young mans beloved Cat turn'd into a Maid, which ſoon ſhewed again her cattiſh diſpoſition, having an opportunity by the ſight of a Mouſe. Some think (I wiſh they be miſtaken) that in regard of the ſpeech and carriage of ſome, that they have a ſecond part to act after the ſame, or a more doleful tune; however it cannot but be good with the ſnake in the fable (who thought her ſelf not ſecure in that houſe wherein the great hatchet was, which had almoſt ſlain her) not to give too much credit to ſuch who have formerly dealt as they have done, error being obſtinate, and making men ſo. <hi>Religio Medici</hi> ſhews the obſtinacy of the Jews in all fortunes, that the perſecution of 1500 years hath but confirmed them in<note place="margin">Page 49.</note> their errors, that they have already endured whatſoever may be inflicted, and have ſuffered abundance, even to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of their enemies; &amp; concludes perſecution to be a bad and indirect way to plant Religion. It is ſo, but means muſt be uſed to preſerve Religion, that we looſe it not.<note place="margin">Society of Saints, p. 29. p. 244. in an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſize Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</note> Some I ſuppoſe will blame me for writing thus now, having formerly pleaded for Puritans, I own what I have written, and wiſh theſe were ſuch, for which I and Mr. <hi>Bolton</hi> plead for; namely practiſing Proteſtants, loyal to Princes, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:41930:48"/> to Laws, juſt, pious, charitable, labouring to be in truth what they ſeem to be; we plead not for factious, ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular, diſorderly followers of <hi>Barrow</hi> and <hi>Greenwood,</hi> the old Puritans being their great oppoſers; I judging with Mr. <hi>Howel,</hi> that the itching of ſcriblers is the ſcab of the times,<note place="margin">Page 62.</note> purpoſed no publication of theſe notes, which made me care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in naming of my Authors, but conſidering that <hi>Nicholas Cauſin</hi> had learned to regard the works of the worſt Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and not to cenſure them; and ſeeing the flame to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe at home and abroad; and thoſe who have much water in their deep wells, and buckets to vent it lie in a ſleep, I have preſumed with my pitcher to ſhew mine endeavour to ſtop and extinguiſh this fire of error; ſome perhaps impute it to dotage, I being well-near ſuch years which are labour and ſorrow, and ſcarce able to go with Crutches; let men think as they pleaſe, my deſire is to cure error, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure order; for which end I will conclude with a paſſage in Mr. <hi>Vines</hi> fore-named Sermon, which is this. If conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence<note place="margin">Page 60.</note> be warrant for practiſes and opinions, and liberty of conſcience be a ſufficient licenſe to vent or act them; I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee but the judicatories either of Church or State may ſhut up their ſhop, and be reſolved into the judicatorie of every mans private conſcience; and put the caſe, that the Magiſtrate ſhould conceive himſelf bound in conſcience to draw forth his Authority againſt falſe teachers, and their damnable hereſies, and (upon that ſuppoſed error) ſhould challenge a liberty of judging, as we do of acting, would our liberty give us any eaſe ſo long as he had his? and were it not better for him to judge, and for us to walk by a known Rule? and if we ſhould ſay that his liberty of judging is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, it is as eaſie for him to ſay, our liberty of Preaching or profeſſing errors is ſo too.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
